<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The composition or making of the moste excellent and pretious oil called oleum magistrale First published by the commaundement of the King of Spain, vvith the maner hovv to apply it particulerly. The which oyl cureth these diseases folowi[n]g ... Also the third book of Galen of curing of pricks and wounds of sinowes. A method for curing of vvounds in the ioynts, and the maner how to place them. Abreef gathering togither of certain errours which the common chirurgians dayly vse ... Faithfully gathered and translated into English by George Baker chirurgian. 1574.</title>
            <author>Baker, George, 1540-1600.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1574</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01943</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1209</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100526</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836363</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836363</idno>
            <idno type="VID">629</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01943)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 629)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 169:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The composition or making of the moste excellent and pretious oil called oleum magistrale First published by the commaundement of the King of Spain, vvith the maner hovv to apply it particulerly. The which oyl cureth these diseases folowi[n]g ... Also the third book of Galen of curing of pricks and wounds of sinowes. A method for curing of vvounds in the ioynts, and the maner how to place them. Abreef gathering togither of certain errours which the common chirurgians dayly vse ... Faithfully gathered and translated into English by George Baker chirurgian. 1574.</title>
                  <author>Baker, George, 1540-1600.</author>
                  <author>Galen. De compositione medicamentorum secundum locos.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 51, [3] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>At the long shop adioyning vnto Saint Mildreds Church in the Pultrie, by Iohn Alde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1574]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With two final leaves of laudatory verse.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Formulae, receipts, prescriptions.</term>
               <term>Orthopedics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:629:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:629:1"/>
            <p>The Compoſition or making of the moſte excellent and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Oil called Oleum Magiſtrale. Firſt publiſhed by the commaundement of the King of Spain, vvith the maner hovv to apply it particulerly. The which Oyl cureth theſe diſſeaſes folowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. That is to ſay, Wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds Contuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Hargubuſh ſhot, Cankerꝭ, pain of the Raines, Apoſtumes, Hemerhoids, olde Vlcers, pain of the Ioints and Gout, and indifferently all maner of diſſeaſes.</p>
            <p>Alſo the third book of Galen of curing of pricks and wounds of Sinowes.</p>
            <p>A method for curing of vvounds in the ioynts, and the maner how to place them.</p>
            <p>A breef gathering togither of certain er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours which the common Chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans dayly vſe. Very profitable and neceſſary for all Chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans &amp; all other which are deſirous to knowe the right method of curing.</p>
            <p>Faithfully gathered and tranſlated into Engliſh by <hi>George Baker Chirurgian. 1574.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>de Vere coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <head>VERO NIHIL VERIVS</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:629:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:629:2"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>TO THE RIGHT honourable Edward de Vere</hi> Earle of Oxford, Vicount Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck, Lord of Eſcales and Badleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere and Lord great Chamberlain of England, his ſinguler good Lord and maiſter, George Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker vvisheth helth, long life vvith much increace of vertue &amp; honor.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T IS NOT vnknowene to any (right honorable) which haue beene but meanly conuerſant in good learning, how far the Gretia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s did ſurmount all the nations of the world in renown of vertue, learning, politique gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and noble victoryes. For what nation dooth not reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce their ſages? what people dooth not
<pb facs="tcp:629:3"/> imbrace their ſtudyes? what Cittie dooth not deſire their gouernment? what prouince was not ſubiect to their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire? yea was not Grecia the Theatre, Spectacle and light of the whole world? were there not in it many famouſe Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties whoſe peple &amp; inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts for ciuilitie, whoſe lawes for policy, whoſe edifices for mag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nificence might ſeem Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall, deuine, and celeſtiall? as Athens and Thebes. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But none more famouſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Cittie of Sparta, whiche by the ſpace of vij. c. yeeres ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled all the Cities of Grecia when they moſte florished, hoth
<pb facs="tcp:629:3"/> in renown of glory and equitie of lawes, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dued: this one cittie Sparta by defending them ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain inuaſion atchiued more ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nor then whole Graecia did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer win by enlargi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g their Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pire. For when Philip of Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cedonia (in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queſt of thoſe Ilandish Cuntreyes and his ſonne Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der after him at the winning of Thebes (were proclamed Emperours of Sea and land, the Spartanes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented not therto nor would be come tributoryes.</p>
            <p>What should be the cauſe that this one Citie should leſse fear the force of Alexander then
<pb facs="tcp:629:4"/> all other? how became it ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expugnable? was it ſo ſtrongly fortified with walles and Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks and warlike munition? not at all. The courage of the Citizens was their onely wall of defence. Did the name of Hercules (whoſe progenie they were) defend them? nay rather the good counſail of Li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>curgus made them invincible? who among other things ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted them to indeuer to excel the whole world in renown of vertue and glory of valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes as their proginitour Her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cules did, whiche if they did not: it were but vain to vaunt of their petydegree.
<pb facs="tcp:629:4"/> Can it be ſaid that the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Citize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g that when by continuall warre the number was greatly dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished and their force much we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kened? Surely by concord they were preſerued.</p>
            <p>Such is the ſtrength that the obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of good lawes doth bring to common welths, ſuch frutes, kindely braunches (not degenerating from a vertuous ſtock) do yeeld, ſuch commody<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties proceed from vertue, and contrary effects from contrary cauſes as may appeer in thoſe ſame Lacedemonians which af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terwards by degeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were brought to the like thraldome
<pb facs="tcp:629:5"/> that their neighbours were in, beeing at length more asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, then proud of their pety degree, more fearful, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> glad of their long reſiſtance. Such alteration folowed the chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of gouernment when no iot of Licurgus lawes, nor any other ſteps of their proginitors ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tues remained among them, but eche man neglected his othe gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen to the common welth, eche man as he was able moſt to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail exerciſed tirany ouer his owne Citizens, eche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that libertie to doo what li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked him, to liue riotouſly and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſly, eche man ſtudied to enrich himſelf, to fortifye his
<pb facs="tcp:629:5"/> owne houſe and to fether his owne neſt. But in the mene time the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth decayed and their forrain ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes increaced, and at length they found by experience how pernitious a thing it is to abro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gate good lawes, to chaunge the countenaunce of a wel go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned ſtate. To race out the memory of their noble proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitors.</p>
            <p>Which example (right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable) I wish to be marked of all noble families and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſe Cities, that therin they may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider that by vertue they are preſerued and by dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration they fall.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:629:6"/>
            <p>Yet doo I not wright theſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs to your honor by the way of exhortation: but rather as a teſtimony of that which is alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to all men, namely to your honors ſtudy carefully to ioyne the commendation of vertue with your nobilitie of blood and linage, whoſe deſire it is (with noble Themiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles) ſo to aduaunce the glory of your cuntrey (wherby your owne honor is the more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent) that no barbarous Siri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phian may vpbraid your honor as though it depended onely of the nobilitie of your country and family, when as if oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie would ſerue your honor
<pb facs="tcp:629:6"/> I dout not would be found in no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble attempts and valeant acts nothing inferiour to Themi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocles.</p>
            <p>In the meane time among in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit tokens: this is one eſpetial ſigne of your honours heroicall minde, that is in courage, acti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uitie and Chiualry, you your ſelf ſeek to expreſse Achilles and other noble perſonages, ſo alſo your honor doth hartely im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brace all ſuche as excel in any worthy vertue, whether it be to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend &amp; adorne her with her ſemly coulours as Homer. &amp;c or to attend like handmaids on her as Hipocrates or Galen with their needful art of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgiry,
<pb facs="tcp:629:7"/> neither dooth your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor ſuffer them to paſse vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, as may appeer by the moſte parte of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which your honor hath entertai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed into your ſeruice as I myſelf haue had experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſince it pleaſed your honor to entertain me (though farre vnworthy) for my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the art of Chirurgiry ſince the which time I haue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted bothe my ſelf and all my labours whatſoeuer, to be due vnto your honor. So that if by continuall ſtudy I might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pely inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or by dayly practiſe in the art of Chirurgery finde out any miſtery which other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me had not obtai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed. I was
<pb facs="tcp:629:7"/> fully purpoſed to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrat and dedicate the ſame vnto your name, not that I am ſo foolish to think that by any my inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; labours any thing shold be added to that huge hepe of your heroycal vertues, but part<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly becauſe (as I haue ſaid) I might tranſfere them to any o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, beeing owing vnto your honor, and partely becauſe the renown of your honours name might obtaine grace for my boldneſse, and bring credit to my labours.</p>
            <p>But in the meane time till I shall be able of myne owne knowledge to ad ſome thing to the perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Art and
<pb facs="tcp:629:8"/> open ſome good rule to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leef of my countreymen: I haue aduentured to interpret one ſmall work of the fatherly both Phiſition and Chirurgion Galen, which I iudged moſte neceſsary for our time, hauing ioyned the ſame with other treatiſes, no leſse fruteful then profitable.</p>
            <p>Which woork although it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth nether with the dignity of your noble name, nor parad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture is anſwerable to your honours oppinion and expecta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of me, and (whiche I must needs confeſse) is ſuperfluous to your honour, who can bothe read and vnderſtand the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:629:8"/> in the firſt tungs wherein the Authors haue written: yet be cauſe other may be releued ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by, I thought I might bothe eaſely obtain pardon, and alſo be bolde to vſe your honours pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tronage in this behalf, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame your honours cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſye and clemencye is vſually extended to all men which doth not vſe to eſteem ſuch gifts as this according to the value, but accepting willingly the good meaning of the perſon.</p>
            <p>Thus beſeeching your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to take in good parte this teſtimony of my thankfull hart ſuche as it is. I beſeech
<pb facs="tcp:629:9"/> alſo the Immortall God to vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the renown of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours name in the noble li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of your noble Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours humble and obedient Seruant George Baker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:629:9"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are two inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> aſwel in Surgery as in all other Arts whereby a man is directed to the ſcope or purpoſe which he intendeth, namely reaſon and experience.</p>
            <p>Reaſon is occupyed about method, and method as <hi>Galen</hi> in the firſt book <hi>De methode medendi</hi> teacheth, is a contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry thing to experience raſhely made and at aduenture, and procéedeth a ſure way taking iudications of the complex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion of the body, of the nature of the deſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed parte, of the cauſes and differences of the diſeaſes and ſo orderly paſſeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudication to iudication applying apt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medyes ſuch as certain experience hath taught to haue vertue correſpondent to ſuch purpoſe as learned method preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, til at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth helth (which is the ſcope and end of the art) be obtained.</p>
            <p>By this diſcription of method: ye may ſée plainly and diſtinctly the vſe and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie bothe of reaſon and experience, but héer muſt you vnderſtand by reaſon ſuch learned iudgement as procedeth by diſcretion and certain knowledge of the
<pb facs="tcp:629:10"/> iudications abooue mentioned, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards maketh apt choiſe of experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>Experience alſo wherof <hi>Galen</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth is a thing of more perfection then the rude obſeruations of vndiſcrete pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſers of our time, but if they would read <hi>Galen</hi> his ſecond book, <hi>De ſimplicium medicamentorium facultatibus.</hi> cap. x. they ſhould learn better what appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to experience how they try and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin their medicins and to iudge true<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly of their vertues. And reaſon applyed to true method is the cauſe of certaintie in Phiſick or Chirurgiry, ſo on the other parte when it is vſed at randon with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out diſcretion and not deriued from true iudication but as fantaſies doo féed the idle brain, it is a thing (as <hi>Galen</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth) ful of great daunger. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he wiſhed the vnlearned practiſers of his time rather to vſe the experience which they knew warely, then to buſy them ſelues with deuiſing euery man a method after his owne way, which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g paſſed their capacitie.</p>
            <p>Such was the method of <hi>Theſſalus</hi> before <hi>Galens</hi> time, and ſuch is the met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hod of <hi>Paracelſus</hi> in our time, but what
<pb facs="tcp:629:10"/> peril did inſue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raſh method of <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſalus:</hi> is by <hi>Galen</hi> in ſundry places de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and how great harme hath béene doon and dayly is committed by the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racelliſtes</hi> both learned <hi>Eraſtus</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſenius</hi> with others doo witneſſe by their writings and dayly experience it ſelf te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acheth.</p>
            <p>And although the common practizers doo by their experience hele many diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: yet as <hi>Galen</hi> ſaith in the ſame firſt Book of his method they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues muſt néeds confeſſe that the ende of their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour dependeth vpon the pleaſure of fortune. For ſithens experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is but the obſeruation or remembrance of the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe had in particuler things as <hi>Galen</hi> him ſelf defineth it, and that neither art nor ſcience conſiſteth in particularities: it muſt néeds folow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> naked experience maketh no art. And then for aſmuch as thoſe which be healed are healed either by art or by chaunce, then it muſt néeds folowe that thoſe which cure by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence without method: doo heal by chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and not by art, and therfore are they wel termed of <hi>Galen</hi> to await the pleaſure of Fortune.</p>
            <p>Thus maiſt thou loouing Reader per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb facs="tcp:629:11"/> what great difference there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him that cureth artificially obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the learned method and order: and the vnſkilful practizer which after ſome fantaſtical deuiſe bred in the braine of the vnlearned or by vndiſcrete expery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence procedeth to the ſame.</p>
            <p>So far dooth the one of theſe differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other, as light from darknes, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge from ignoraunce, order from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and to conclude: certaintie from vncertaintie or blinde chaunce. Now let the ſick man be iudge, whether is for him the more ſafetie tobe heled orderly, artificially and ſurely: or to depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpon the haſard of blinde Fortune, happy or not happy, at aduenture whether yea or nay. But if ye beleeue <hi>Hipocrates. Age re foeliciter eſt agere prudenter et age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re infoeliciter eſt agere imprudenter,</hi> to be happy is to be ſkilful, and to deale vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>luckely is to deale vnſkilfully. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue many obſeruations of the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſes of many men perceiuing yea almoſte dayly great errours committed in many things concerning mine art of Chirurgery for lack of true method, and that moſte of all in the wounds of ioints and Sinewes or Sinewy, or muſculous
<pb facs="tcp:629:11"/> places whiche require peculter &amp; diſtinct method &amp; order of cure from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wounds of other fleſhly places, and the ſame béeing more painful, and for the greatnes of the accidents which folowe them béeing of far more daunger doo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire therefore the greater care &amp; more artificiall handling then any other.</p>
            <p>I haue therfore for looue I bere to my facultie, which I wiſh void of infamy, and for the harty deſire I bere to the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fit of ſuch as be hurt and diſeaſed, inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured to ſet foorth ſome thing in our engliſh tung, as thoſe which are willing to learn: might therby be inſtructed and directed to the true method and trade of curing the ſaid wounds of Sinowes. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> requireth in Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy: the ſame I think alſo in Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery moſte neceſſary. <hi>Vt exempla ſunt non chaerilia ſed homerica,</hi> that is, not to folowe the practiſe of bunglers or the vnſkilful ſort, but to learne at the beſt learned.</p>
            <p>Then for aſmuch as <hi>Galen</hi> by the Iudgement of the learned of all nations hath excelled all other that haue writen in Phiſick but cheefely in his method: I thought good to tranſlate into our natiue
<pb facs="tcp:629:12"/> tung, his third Booke of the compoſition of medicines accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to places, wherin bothe learned &amp; abundantly he teacheth the curing of theſe wounds whiche my labour taking for the furtherance of ſuch as be willing to learne to doo wel, if it be on thy parte (moſte loouing Reader) wel accepted: I haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> héerin my deſire as for the wilful ignorant I leaue to them ſelues.</p>
            <p>And thus beſéeching God to bleſſe the handy woork of ſuche as faithfully and charitably deale in the affaires of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſick and diſeaſed: I reſt to trouble thée any longer from the reading bothe of the compoſition of the moſte pretious Oil called <hi>Oleum Magiſtrale:</hi> and alſo of <hi>Galen</hi> him ſelf.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my houſe in Lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don <date>the xv. of Marche 1574.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:629:12"/>
            <head>The Preface to the <hi>Book.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Realme</hi> of Spain there inhaby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a people called in the Spaniſh tung <hi>Moriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> of the which nation this Oyl was firſt pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, vnknowen to the Spaniards: which afterwards came to their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding by the baptiſed <hi>Affricans,</hi> of the which nation there are a great number in <hi>Granado</hi> and <hi>Aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan,</hi> and as yet they folow the orders of the Turks, bothe in their meats, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel and language, and haue no affinitie with the Spaniards, but only that they be baptized and become Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. And although they be not as yet growen ſo ſuttle &amp; crafty as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Spaniards: yet neuertheleſſe it hath béene wel prooued and ſéen by experience that they haue had more knowledge then the ſaid Spa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niards, both in the ſecrets of nature, and alſo in the properties of herbs and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in the art of curing.</p>
            <p>In this ſaid nation, there was one na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Aparice,</hi> the which about the yéere
<pb facs="tcp:629:13"/> of our Lord, 1566. did take his dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling place at <hi>Madrid</hi> a town ſituated in <hi>Caſtille la neufeue,</hi> 12 legues from <hi>Tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leta,</hi> at the which place the court is moſt commonly kept: where he did think beſt to be for his profit, and there did begin to practiſe the art of Chirurgery and to cure Wounds, Contuſions, Hargubuſh ſhot, Canckers, pain of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Rains, Apoſtumes, Hemorhoids, olde Vlcers, pain of the gout, and indifferently all maner of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, ſo that within ſhort time he did ſuch cures worthy of praiſe that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (hauing intelligence of his merue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous experience) reſorted vnto him thrée ſcore miles about, to the end that by his help they might receiue their helth. And after that he had healed them: he delt ſo fauourably with them, that moſte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly he took leſſe then they did offer vnto him, and healed them in viij. dayes which the Chirurgians of the Towne could not doo in iij. wéeks.</p>
            <p>In ſo much that he was eſtéemed of all men, aſwel for the excellency of his art: as alſo for his great curteſy whiche he ſhewed vnto them.</p>
            <p>Yet neuertheles as we ſée that ſcience and vertue is neuer peaceable (although
<pb facs="tcp:629:13"/> that the common people were wel certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of his labour and ſeruice) yet the M. Chirurgians of the town (féeling their perticuler profit and authoritie to decay by this aforſaid <hi>Aparice</hi>) began to be at great ſtrife with him, and ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moned him to appéer before the <hi>Alcaldes,</hi> which are the Iudges of the aforeſaid town, ſaying that he did them great iniury &amp; wrong in medling with the art of the which he had no knowledge, which art did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain onely to them béeing ſworn to that facultie, and that they would bring in good proof in the common welth, that hée did more harme then good. So that their deſire was to haue him impriſoned, to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that if he ſhould fear any thing in the meane time, to abſent him ſelf, and alſo laying many haynous crymes againſt him. The Iudges could doo no leſſe then commit him to priſon.</p>
            <p>Vpon whoſe impriſonment: certain gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and others (which hauing by his meanes receiued their helth of great hurts and diſeaſes, and regarding the profit of the common welth, and alſo ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great wrong which the ſaid Chi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rurgians vſed againſt the ſaid <hi>Aparice,</hi> béeing ſo honeſt and vpright in his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<pb facs="tcp:629:14"/> concerning his art, &amp; that nothing which was laid againſt him could be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued: thought among them ſelues that he deſerued a better rewarde then he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued at their hands.</p>
            <p>Whervpon they made with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent a Supplication in his behalf for the bayling of him out of priſon, the whiche (by reaſon of his long béeing ſick in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) they obtained vpon that condition that hee ſhould medle no more with any cures, vntil ſuche time as he were authoriſed.</p>
            <p>Yet neuertheleſſe many diſeaſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons béeing afflicted with diuers greefs, would not abſtain from him, but reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him dayly, the which he would not by any meanes medle with for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his great charge that he had to the contrary, yet not withſtanding the importaunce of the people was ſo great: that he was conſtrayned ſecretly to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter vnto them.</p>
            <p>The which at length was diſcloſed vnto the Chirurgians of the town, and immediatly after they made their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint to the aforeſaid Iudges and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared vnto them that the ſaid <hi>Aparice</hi> had doon contrary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> order y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was made
<pb facs="tcp:629:14"/> wherupon he was committed to priſon again, which cauſed that the whole aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of the town bothe Gentlemen, Burgeſſes &amp; merchants (in his behalf) complained to the Iudges, in ſo muche that in th' end it came to the kings eare, which beeing a wiſe prince and deſiring the profit of his common welth: was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to knowe the aforeſaid Priſoner, and the true &amp; right cauſe in all things.</p>
            <p>And when he vnderſtood the iuſt cauſe and that whiche the ſaid <hi>Aparice</hi> did, was by the vertue of a ſimple Oyl: he was deſirous to knowe the compoſition of it. The which the ſaid <hi>Aparice</hi> (what for the gréef of his wrongful impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the vncurteous dealing of the Chirurgians) refuſed to declare, ſaying that it was the meanes wherby he did get his liuing, ſo that if it were common<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly knowen: it would be an occaſion that he ſhould be no more ſought vnto.</p>
            <p>When the King perceiued that hee could not obtain it: he offred vnto him (in conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he ſhould ſhew the receipt) a thouſand Duckets, which the ſaid <hi>Aparice</hi> refuſed, ſaying that he did holde him ſelf better conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with his ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence then he could with golde &amp; Siluer.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:629:15"/>
            <p>So that immediatly folowing the ſaid <hi>Aparice</hi> (béeing very ſore ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his foreſaid ſicknes, and partly for the gréef that he took of his wrongfull impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) ended his life, for the which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny noble perſonages did much lament, thinking that with his dead carkas: this noble treaſure ſhould haue béen buryed, and alſo the king him ſelf was very ſore greeued for the loſſe of ſuche a rare and precious ſcience.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe the ſaid <hi>Aparice</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing maried a Spaniſh woman (by the which he had certain children) declared the ſecret of this pretious Oyl vnto her as ſhalbe ſhewed héer after.</p>
            <p>Immediatly after the death of the ſaid <hi>Aparice,</hi> the king beeing very ſory be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he could not get the knowledge of ſuch a ſcience: made a diligent ſerch to knowe if their were any of his fréends which had this ſecret medicine, and alſo to knowe whether his wife had it, to the which they all anſwered that there was none other that euer had the knowledge therof but onely he him ſelf, and that he kept it from his owne wife, for fear leſt ſhe ſhould (béeing a woman) diſcloſe it and make it common although ſhe dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſed
<pb facs="tcp:629:15"/> patients in her huſbands abſence, and alſo whileſt he was priſoner.</p>
            <p>At his laſt impriſonment, he féeling him ſelf not like to liue becauſe of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering that he ſhould leue his wife and Children but in a wofull ſtate: diſcouered this ſecret vnto her, and did leaue it vnto her for a pretious trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and there withall gaue her a great charge that ſhe ſhould not diſcloſe it to any man, what ſoeuer ſhuld be offred vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to her for it.</p>
            <p>But as in the end all things come to light, ſhe (for to get her owne lyuing and her poor Childrens) began to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medle for to cure ſecretly with the ſaid Oyl and ſolde it vnto them whiche ſtood in néed of it, ſaying that it was of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Oyl that her huſband had made.</p>
            <p>Not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people (perceiued that it laſted very long &amp; that it could not be choſen but that ſhe muſt haue the receit) offred vnto her for the compoſition ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, fiue hundred duckets, but ſhe anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that ſhe had it not, and ſaid if ſhe had it: ſhe would rather dye then declare it.</p>
            <p>For the cauſe of the which ſharp an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere: ſhe was expreſly inhibited from curing with the ſaid Oil, neither to ſel it
<pb facs="tcp:629:16"/> for any maner price. By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which menes (what with the councell of her freends and neceſſitie conſtrayning her) ſhe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred to declare the the ſecret, in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration that ſhe might haue the thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Duckets, but in th'end ſhe was conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to take fiue hundred Duckes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the King graunted in the preſence of certain Phiſitions and Chirurgians which were appointed, vnto whome ſhe declared the ſecret and ſhewed by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience the compoſition and the manner how to make it.</p>
            <p>And they to prooue whether it were the ſame or no: applyed it to many diſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed perſons, and it was found of the ſame vertue and effect of that that her huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d had made. And then was named by the Phiſitions and Chirurgians the Oyl <hi>Magiſtrale,</hi> eſtéeming it to be the beſt and moſte pretious among all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>So that when they had iuſtly approoued that it was the very ſame ſecret that her huſband left vnto her: they deliuered vnto her the fiue hundred Duckets whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che the King promiſed vnto her.</p>
            <p>Then by the commandement of the King: the Phiſitions and Chirurgians
<pb facs="tcp:629:16"/> of the Town had the perfit knoweledge of it, in ſuch ſort, that at this preſent day almoſte all the whole Realme of Spain vſeth none other medicines, what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of hurt or wound ſo euer it bee, whiche is a moſte excellent and approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>Mitigatiue</hi> or appeaſer of pain, and is a very good ſecret neceſſary tobe kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen in a common welth.</p>
            <p>And as for my parte: I would it were aſwell knowen and experimented in this Realme as it is there. Therfore for the good wil and affection the whiche I bere towardes my countrey (to the which I am bound to ſerue to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte of my power) I thought good to write this ſecret and to bring it to light, although I knowe that there be ſome which wil not be wel pleaſed heerwith, and paraduenture wil demaund of me the experience of it, for the whiche I doo not force ſéeing that I haue the trueth on my ſide, and that it is not vnknowen to a great number (which haue traue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Realme of Spain) the nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſinguler vertues of this Oyle, the which they doo dayly ſel to all other Nations, and I my ſelf hauing ſéene the notable vertues therof approoued vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:629:17"/> diuers of our owne nation, at the hands bothe of Merchants and Marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners which brought the ſaid Oyle from thence.</p>
            <p>And now chauncing with the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of the making of the ſaid Oyle, and béeing ſo wel aſſured, that it is the right and perfet order, and for the which I wil anſwere: I thought it my dutie to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe ſuch a noble ſecret, for the profit of ſo many as I knowe ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ayd therby, rather then to pleaſe ſome perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler perſons.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:629:17"/>
            <head>The compoſition of the Oyle called <hi>Oleum Magiſtrale</hi> inuented by one named <hi>Aparice.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt you shall take</hi> a quarte of the beſt and oldeſt white wine y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may be gotten, Oil Olif of the oldeſt iij. pound then put therto theſe floures &amp; herbs folowing, to wit. The floures and leaues of <hi>Hiperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi> half a l. <hi>Cardus benedictus,</hi> a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a l. <hi>Valerian</hi> a quarter of a l. of the leaſt Sage a quarter of a l. of euery one of theſe you ſhall take the leaues &amp; flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers if it be poſſible. Then let all theſe ſtéep xxiiij. houres in the aforeſaid wine and Oile, the next day boile them in a nealed pot or in a copper veſſel, vpon a ſoft fire vntil ſuch time as the wine be al conſumed, alwaies ſtirring it with a Spattle.</p>
            <p>After you haue thus doon: take it from the fire and ſtrain it, and to the ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: put a l. and a half of good <hi>Venice</hi> Turpentine, then boile it again vpon a ſoft fire the ſpace of a quarter of an hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, then ad therto <hi>Olibanum</hi> v. vnces, <hi>Mirrah</hi> iij. vnces. <hi>Sanguis draconis.</hi> one
<pb facs="tcp:629:18"/> vnce, and ſo let it boil til the Ince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and the <hi>Mirrah</hi> be diſſolued, then take it of and let it ſtand til it be colde, then put it into a glaſſe Bottle and ſet it viij. or x. dayes in the Sun and keep it to your vſe.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>The maner to apply the ſaide Oyl according to the qualities of the vvounds or diſeaſes, dooth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in theſe vi. thingꝭ folowing.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ To the patient, to the preparatife, to the wound, or diſeaſe, to the plaiſter and to the diſeaſed parte.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt the hurted and afflicted par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie muſt vſe this Regiment folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing, that is to ſay, to kéep no ſtraight diet, neither in eating nor drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for fear of weakning the body and hindring of his helth. So that he may eat and drink, as he was accuſtomed to doo before he was hurt. As for example, he may eat to his dinner new laid Eggꝭ, Mutton, wilde foule of the woods, princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally when they haue bled, and likewiſe at night ye may roſte any of theſe, and if he were accuſtomed to eat groſe meatꝭ in his helth, as Porke, Onions, Garlick
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:629:18"/> and ſuch like, he néed not to forbere them but to vſe them according as his apetite wil ſerue him and alſo to drinck wines, if he haue vſed them before he was hurt.</p>
                  <p>Yet neuertheles if he be a body filled with humours, and giuen to a Feuer or any other inconuenience: he muſt vſe his meats and drincks with diſcretion, and if he drinck any wine it muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed with water. Notwithſtanding <hi>Aparice</hi> did neuer forbid any kindes of meats to his patients which they were accuſtomed to vſe in their helth.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, if the wound be great: the patient ought to kéep his bed, if he cannot kéep his bed: yet at the leaſt he muſt kéep his Chamber without taking any ayre which might anoy him.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, hee muſt kéep an order in his lying, that is to ſay, he may not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies lye on one ſide: but ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> turn from one ſide to an other, aſwel vpon the wun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded part as otherwiſe, and eſpetially an houre before he be dreſt, to the end that the humours may diſcend to the gréef, which ought to be vſed in wounds aſwel with cuts as with pricks as ſhalbe ſaid in his proper place.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, he muſt indure the Oil as
<pb facs="tcp:629:19"/> hot as euer it can be poſſible, for it is the nature of the Oile tobe applyed ſeething hot, for the hotter he is applyed: the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger he is in operation. It is néedful alſo that he abſtain from the company of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men for becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it would bring great inconueniences vnto him, and not for the time of his healing: but alſo xx. dayes after, and principally if the wound were great.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="preparation">
                  <head>¶ A Preparatif.</head>
                  <p>TO prepare the wound before the ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plying of the Oil, you ſhall take good white wine and boil it with one handful of Encence, (which is onely to comfort) with the which you ſhall waſh the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d as hot as the Patient can ſuffer, bothe within and without, then wipe it very wel with a clene linen cloth before that you apply the Oyl, which ſhalbe ſhewed héerafter, the occaſion and the time how to apply it: and when the afore ſaid waſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing ſhall not be vſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of the Oyle.</head>
                  <p>THe ſaid Oil, the more older it is: the better it is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and of the greater effect. And you ſhall remember (as before hath
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:629:19"/> béen ſaid) to apply it as hot as may be, for by this meanes he ſhal the finelier perce and heale the wound the ſooner.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The time of dreſſing of the wound.</head>
                  <p>IT is neceſſarye that if the wound come by any bitings or brooſings: that he be dreſſed twiſe a day, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to all other as ſhalbe ſaid heerafter.</p>
                  <p>That is to ſay, in winter at viij. of the clock in the morning, and at thrée of the clock at night. And in Summer at ix. of the clock in the morning, and at iiij. at night, becauſe they be the moſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent houres. But if they be gréen wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds: after the firſt dreſſing you ſhall not néed to chaunge it again vntil the next day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ The differences of diſeaſes.</head>
                  <p>THe wounds &amp; diſeaſes doo differ, for ſome are olde &amp; ſome are new, ſome in one parte and ſome in an other, as in the hed, armes or legs, and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for the which the wounds doo differ, as ſhalbe ſhewed héerafter of euery one particulerly, and alſo the maner &amp; vſage to applye the ſaid Oile according to the maner, and gréef of the diſeaſed parte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:629:20"/>
                  <head>¶ The vſe of the Implaiſter that is to be applyed with the Oyle vpon the diſeaſed parte.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt for wounds of the hed, you ſhall ſhaue away the heare ij. or iij. fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers breadth round about the wound.</p>
                  <p>And then ſtay the blood with lint or tow beeing dipt in the ſaid Oyle, with the which you ſhall fil the wound, and vpon that apply a linnen cloth ij. or thrée dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which ſhall couer all the place, (as far as the here hath béen ſhauen away) beeing ſteped in the prepared wine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, and afterwards wrung out then role it vp. This is it that ought tobe applyed at the firſt dreſſing. Alſo this is tobe vnderſtanded, that at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt dreſſing: the prepared wine ought not to bee vſed for feare of cauſing the flux of blood.</p>
                  <p>Alſo you ſhal note that if the wound be very great, or in a daungerous place, by the which meanes there might enſue a flux of blood: you ſhall dreſſe it but once a day at the firſt and ſecond dreſſing, and from that time foreward, at euery dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſing you ſhall waſh the wound with the prepared Wine aforeſaid bothe within and without, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wipe it very clene with
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:629:20"/> a fine linnen cloth that the wound may be made clene within and without, for it is very néedful.</p>
                  <p>Then afterwarde you ſhall fill the wound with Oyle and couer it with lint ſtéeped in the ſame, and vpon that again apply a linne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cloth ij or iij. double round about beeing dipt in the ſaid ſaid Oyle.</p>
                  <p>And then vpon that again lay an other cloth moiſtened in the ſaid Wine and wrung as aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>This is the particuler order of all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wounds and muſt be vſed til ſuch time as you perceiue the wound is vpon healing, and then you ſhall heale it vp with this Vnguent folowing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ The manner to make the Vnguent and how it ought tobe vſed.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the ſaid Oile <hi>Magiſtrale, Ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nis</hi> Turpentine and new Wax, of eche like quantitie, ſet it on the fire in a little pan, alwaies ſtirring it the ſpace of a quarter of an houre. Then take it from the fire and let it cool, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is colde: put it in a box and kéep it to your vſe.</p>
                  <p>And when you ſhall haue occaſion ſo vſe it: it wil ſerue bothe for the Vnguent, and the Implaiſter. You ſhall apply the
<pb facs="tcp:629:21"/> Vnguent vpon Lint and lay it to the gréef, and afterwards a little dry Lint vpon that, and then applye vpon that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain an Implaiſter made with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Vnguent,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Heer foloweth the particuler orders how to apply this Oile Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le in euery diſeaſe</head>
                  <p>FOr wounds of the head, you muſt haue a good conſideration whether it were doon with ſtone, ſtaffe or fall, or ſuch other like accidents which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called contuſions. So that if the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d be healed vp, and that there be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendered any Apoſtume or accidents (which may chaunce by contuſion or bru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> veſſels or breking of the bones) it would be a great offence to the brain.</p>
                  <p>Wherfore to auoide ſuch inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, you ſhall order it in this ſort, that is, you wall ſhaue the heare of the place round about it, and then waſh it very wel with the ſaid Wine, then wipe it very clene, and anoint it round about with the ſaid Oile, and lay round about it linnen clothes ſtéeped in the ſaid Oile, and vpon that again other linne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clothes ſtéeped in the ſaid wine, which ſhalbe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:629:21"/> vſed for the ſpace of v. or vi. dayes or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the gréef of the place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For vvounds of the legges.</head>
                  <p>IF the wound be in any of the legs, and the muſcles or ſinewye partes, béeing cut ouerthwart: it muſt be ſtiched according to the bignes of the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, or if there be any diſlocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bone: you ſhal place him in his due order after the beſt maner. Then you ſhall waſh the wound bothe within and without with the ſaid wine, &amp; if you fear any accidents whiche might happen by th'offence of the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d; you ſhal waſh the whole member w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſaid wine. As if it be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> arme, from the ſhoulder to the fingers ends, &amp; if it be in the thigh: down to the ends of the toes. Afterwards anoint the whole member with the ſaid Oile &amp; ſay round about it a linne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cloth ſteeped in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Oil, &amp; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> another double cloth beeing ſteeped in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aforſaid wine &amp; wrung. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> role it in ſuch ſort y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it be neither to ſtraight nor to ſlack, &amp; as for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cure: you ſhall finiſh it in ſuch order as hath been ſhewed before in the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hed, but if it chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that the wound be very great and that there be loce bones which muſt be had out: you ſhall apply a tent in the
<pb facs="tcp:629:22"/> lower parte of the wound, for feare leſt the wound ſhould ſhut vp to ſoon, and by that meanes might fall to ſome incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience. Therfore you ſhall keep in the tent til ſuch time, as you haue taken out all ſuch things as is againſt nature.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of wounds made with Hargubush and thruſts with Swoords, Pikes, and ſuch other like.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt it is neceſſary to ſtay the flux of blood as before hath béene ſaid in wounds of the hed, then waſh the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with the foreſaid wine and wipe it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry clene. And if it fortune that the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d perce through the member: you ſhall tent bothe ſides of the wound, according to the length therof, to the end that you may purge the wound of Contuſion or bruſed blood, which might remain in it &amp; ſo to be dreſt twiſe a day. And you ſhall dreſſe bothe ſides of the wound, as before hath béen ſaid, bothe in the waſhing and anointing. And if it be ſo that the wound perce through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body: you ſhall tye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tent with a threed leſt it ſhould ſlip into the body and ſo anoy the Patient. And alſo day by day as occaſion ſhall ſerue to ſhor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten the Tent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:629:22"/>
                  <head>Of ſvvellings and Apoſtumations.</head>
                  <p>IN what part of the body ſoeuer ther chaunce any Apoſtume or ſwelling whether that it wil come to matter or re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolue: you ſhall hathe the greeued place with the aforeſaid wine, being warmed and lay theron linnen clothes (béeing ſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped in the ſaid wine and wrong) a good breadth round about the place, as before hath béen ſaid. And if you ſee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it reſolue: apply the ſayd Oile and wine vntil ſuch time as it be whole. And if it come to ſuppuration: you ſhall vſe it as before hath béen taught.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ For the Hemerhoids.</head>
                  <p>YOu ſhall waſh them with the fore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaid wine, and then apply your Oil with linnen clothes, as afore ſaid and pvon that your prepared Wine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For colde Gouts.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt you ſhall anoint all the whole greeued place with the ſaid Oil, then apply linnen clothes vpon that, béeing ſteped in ſcalding water, and wrung very hard. This doon thrée or foure times: ſhall ceaſe the pain.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:629:23"/>
                  <head>¶ For Cankers.</head>
                  <p>IF the Canker be not opened: the waſhing with the ſaid Wine, and the pledgets ſtéeped in the ſaid Oil and applyed wil cauſe him to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and when be is opened, you ſhall proſecute the cure as afore hath béen ſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For pain in the Raines.</head>
                  <p>YOu ſhall anoint the Raines very wel with the ſaid Oil from the ridge of the back to the belly, then vpon that apply a linnen cloth béeing ſteped in ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing water and wrung hard as before hath been ſaid, &amp; vpon that again great pledgets of Towe, and you ſhall wrap his legges very warme with hot clothes and let him lye down vpon his bed and couer him warme, then wil he begin to ſwete, which ſweate wilbe an occaſion of his helth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ For olde Vlcers.</head>
                  <p>YOu ſhall firſt cut the lips of the Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer with a very ſharp Razur, then waſh it very wel with the foreſaid wine and ſo finiſh the reſt of the cure as before hath béen ſaid.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:629:23"/>
            <head>¶ Galenes third Book of the compoſition of medicens.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Alen (the father</hi> and light of Phiſick) ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great abuſe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che was in his time in the curing of wounds and hurts of <hi>Nerues</hi> or Sinewes: thought it neceſſary (in this his third Book of the compoſition of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicens) generally to intreate and write the method or maner of curing wounds in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Nerues</hi> or Sinewye partes, which cure before <hi>Galenes</hi> time was much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, and many patients ſuffered bothe terrible torments with loſſe of their lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and alſo gréeuous conuolſions and painful cramps, not without dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous feuers and great putrifaction, haſtening vntimely death.</p>
            <p>So that there was none that had the perfect cure therof, for at the beginning: they vſed conglutinatiue and knitting medicins,<note place="margin">The errors which haue been vſed before Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens time.</note> which they ought not to haue doon. And if there chaunced any infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: then they fomented the afflicted place with hot water, and applyed <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plaſmus</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:629:24"/> of whete meale, boyled with <hi>Hedraelaeum,</hi> that is to ſay Oil and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter boyled togither, in the which was a great error and contrary to all true me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, for in ſo dooing: the diſeaſed parte quickly corrupted, and came to putrifa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, by reaſon of vnnatural heat and to much moiſture,<note place="margin">Hot and moiſt inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth putri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>faction and corruption.</note> which are the onely and cheefeſt cauſes of putrifaction.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe it dooth not followe that at all times drying &amp; cooling things ought tobe vſed, becauſe that the colde is an enemy to the Sinewes,<note place="margin">Hip. lib. 5 Aphoriſ 20.</note> as <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> teſtifieth, wherfore there muſt be vſed drying things tempered with mode rate heat, or at the leaſt more declyning to heat then to colde, which ought tobe of a ſuttle and percing ſubſtance, for heate alone dooth not ingender putrifaction, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be mixt with abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dant moiſture.</p>
            <p>And after theſe things béeing well conſidered: there muſt be diligent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde whether the Sinew be vncouered or not,<note place="margin">Method for the cure of Nerues.</note> for if the ſinew be vncouered: the medicen ought not to be ſo ſtrong, for in ſuch a caſe, gentle and milde medicens are moſt meet where the Sinew is bare otherwiſe it wil bring moſte perrillous accidents.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:629:24"/>
            <p>Theſe medicens that are héer reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are of a thin ſuttle ſubſtance or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as <hi>Succus cerenaeus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>culties of Simples, which muſt be vſed in theſe medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens.</note> 
               <hi>Succus medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, Sagapenum</hi> of the Eaſt <hi>Euphorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> of the Weſt, and the iuce of <hi>Tithi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males.</hi> Of minerals or medicens which are found in the Earth, ſome be very ſut<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle as <hi>Aphromtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> id eſt Nitri ſpuma,</hi> the frothy parte of <hi>Nitrum,</hi> which eaſely wil diſſolue or be melted in water. Like wiſe theſe are ſuttle, <hi>Nitrum beroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi> and <hi>Aſia Petra,</hi> the floure of which among all earthly medicens is the moſt ſuttle. Of metalls <hi>Lorpin</hi> and <hi>Sulphur</hi> be both ſuttle and hot. After theſe <hi>Miſy, verdigrece</hi> and <hi>Chalcitis</hi> a mineralls of Lime, the which be very hot and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what aſtringaunt.</p>
            <p>Therfore in the compounding of ſuche ſuttle medicamentꝭ: we commonly burn or at the leaſt waſh and ſuch like to miti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gate the ſircenes of their coroſiue &amp; fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting nature as <hi>Chalcitis.</hi> And next to this are placed <hi>Spodium, Pompholix, Pſoicum</hi> &amp; <hi>Chriſocolla,</hi> medicens of ſut<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle ſubſtance, without any ſmarting heate. And of the like qualities are <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus laurinus</hi> and <hi>Cedrinus,</hi> that is to ſay the iuce of <hi>Bayes</hi> and <hi>Cedre.</hi> Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:629:25"/> the <hi>Bay</hi> is not ſo ſuttle as the <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre.</hi> And of the like qualities and kindes is the licour or water of <hi>Lixiuii</hi> whiche the <hi>Greeks</hi> call <hi>Stacta,</hi> and yet Oile of <hi>Cedron</hi> is of a greater and more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vertue, although that the ſaid <hi>Lix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuii</hi> be made of ſuttle things moſte fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and artificially burnt.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The compoſition of this ſaid Lixiuii.</head>
               <p>Is of a wilde Figge trée, whiche the <hi>Greeks</hi> call <hi>Erineon,</hi> and of <hi>Tithimales</hi> burnt. The beſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid <hi>Tithimales</hi> is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which the Gréeks call <hi>Characias,</hi> which is the male &amp; the greateſt moouer. The Corne which the Greeks call <hi>Sitera</hi> that is to ſay Whete, and <hi>Eruus</hi> or <hi>Orobus</hi> is the moſte ſuttleleſt, conſidering that they haue no great facultie to heate.</p>
               <p>You ſhall vnderſtand that the moſte parte of Simples whiche are ſuttle and fine are hot. And thoſe which are of gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, colde, the reaſon is euident, for the heate is ſuttle and light, and the colde: thick and heauy, and dooth bothe repreſſe and binde togithers.</p>
               <p>Yet for all that ſome colde Simples haue a ſharp qualitie with ſuttle ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, yet in operation it is cooling, as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:629:25"/> Vinagre,<note place="margin">Cold is an agent qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie aſwel as heate.</note> for among all the Simples it is moſte ſuttleſt.</p>
               <p>Therfore it is neceſſary to haue good knoweledge in the nature and qualitye of ſimples,<note place="margin">Method for the knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and facultie of Simples and how they muſt be vſed.</note> wherof medicens haue their béeing. For without the knowledge ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of: it is not poſſible to doo any thing in this art, and eſpecially in the cure of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes worthy commendation. It ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to haue great ſtore of Receipts, except ye knowe the particuler nature of euery ſimple. And with hauing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: he ſhalbe able to frame his compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition him ſelf, according as the nature of the gréef ſhall require.</p>
               <p>The parfit knoweledge of Simples is in thrée thinges, that is to ſay, of plants, of metalles, and of liuing things, and it is not ſufficient to ſée them once or twiſe:<note place="margin">Euery this in his time</note> but you muſt marke and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde them often, as in their beginning, growing, ſtate, and declination.<note place="margin">All things are kept in their place out of the which as ſoon as it is remoued it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more ſubiect tobe corrupted.</note> For by this beholding: you ſhall knowe in what time it is beſt to gather them, if they be not gathered in their due time: the heat of the Sun will burne and take away their vertue. And alſo the place where they muſt be kept ought tobe temperate in heat &amp; moiſture, for feare of chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging
<pb facs="tcp:629:26"/> their nature or vertue, for without the knowledge therof it is not poſſible for a Chirurgian to haue the true vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing and method to compound medicens nor to gouerne well the curation of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes.</p>
               <p>So then it is neceſſary to knowe the nature and facultye of Simples whiche is amply ſhewed in many good Bookes and eſpecially by <hi>Galen</hi> in his Booke of Simples.</p>
               <p>I finde a certain hiſtory in the fore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaid Author the which I think may wel and fitly be reherſed in this place,<note place="margin">The hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for an ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ample of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ioints.</note> to make this more plain to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reader. Vpon a certain time there was brought to <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>len</hi> a childe, hauing a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or brooſe vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on the firſt ioynte of his middle finger in ſuch ſort y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the whole ioint began to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifye &amp; corrupt, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Galen</hi> applyed to the putrified parte a <hi>Cataplaſme</hi> or <hi>Pultiſe,</hi> made with Barly mele &amp; wax, &amp; fome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted it with the <hi>Lixiuii</hi> rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted place, but where there was gréefe and pain: he made fome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tation with hote Oyle, and then after the moiſture was drawen out, by the applying of dry wul, he vſed a medicine made with Oil, wax and <hi>Euphorbium,</hi> by the which meanes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:629:26"/> he preſerued the ioynt. The like he did to an other which came to him in win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which had great colde with pain in his Knée continually, the which he cured in like maner with Oile and <hi>Euphor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium,</hi> for the Sinewes and tendones<note place="margin">The ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dones are dryer then the ſinewes</note> doo receiue all one curation, and the acci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dents that chaunceth to the one: chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth to th'other. For the names of ſuch paſſions or gréefs it is no matter, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not the names that doo either good or harme. But it is the facultie of the medicins which doth all. Let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the cure.</p>
               <p>Afterwards the ſaid Childes finger began to putrifie more and more, and he began to féel pain and gréef vpwarde in the whole places. Then <hi>Galen</hi> in the place of Barly mele: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tenth day, did vſe the mele of <hi>Orobus</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſaid <hi>Lixiuii,</hi> or <hi>Stacta</hi> wherewith the Patient be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to amend,<note place="margin">Stacte was made of ſtilled wild Fig leaues</note> and within iij. dayes was eaſed of his pain, ſauing that there remai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bruſed place, a certain <hi>Neruous</hi> or knotty ſubſtance muche like vnto a great tendone y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which was redy to fall, &amp; after béeing half rotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: fel all togithers, which did make many think, ſeeing this knotty ſubſtance: that the Sinew had
<pb facs="tcp:629:27"/> béen altogithers rotten, which was for lack of the knoweledge of their Anotho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and for lack of that knowledge they did not conſider how the Tendones<note place="margin">The ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dones and their citua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> or Cordes are couered with the ſaid <hi>Ner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, Membrana</hi> as defenſatiues, not only throughout the inſide of the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence go in order to all the fingers.</p>
               <p>Then after that <hi>Galene</hi> had taken away that which was putrified from the ſaid brooſe: the corde was very ſound and clene, &amp; then he vſed <hi>Troſis</hi> diſſolued in <hi>Sapa,</hi> &amp; applyed it in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foreſaid <hi>Neruous</hi> parte, &amp; made particuler vnction again and in like maner vſed the <hi>Pultis,</hi> and the anointing with <hi>Euphorbium</hi> as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid. And when he had thus doon: the fourth day, did think with him ſelf what medicin that were beſt then to applye, and conſidering that if there were no inflamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or diſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perance: it were beſt to apply ſkinning things, but if there were any inflamation: then he thought beſt to vſe moderate drying things with out <hi>Cicatriſing</hi> or ſkinning.</p>
               <p>And when he did ſee there was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamation: he vſed the medicament that is called the gréen Plaiſter of <hi>Epigoni,</hi> which the Gréeks call <hi>Iſis.</hi> The whiche
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:629:27"/> Emplaiſter you ſhall finde in his ſecond book of compoſition of medicins in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, then afterwards for to finiſh the cure: he vſed an other medicine compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as foloweth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rec.</hi> of wax, <hi>drachmas</hi> 150. <hi>Tereben thinae, drachm.</hi> 200, <hi>Seui vitulini, drach<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mas.</hi> 50. <hi>Galbani, drachmas</hi> 24. <hi>Manne thuris, drachmas</hi> 24. <hi>Salis amoniaci, drachmas</hi> 12. <hi>Aeris vſti, drachmas</hi> 12. <hi>Aloes, drachmas.</hi> 12. <hi>Squame aeris, drach<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mas</hi> 24. <hi>Alluminis rotundi, drachmas</hi> 24. <hi>Alum plu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, drachmas</hi> 8, <hi>Chalchitis drachmas.</hi> 8. <hi>Miſeos. draehmas</hi> 8. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>popenex, drachmas</hi> 8. <hi>Erui, drachmas</hi> 6. <hi>Ammoniaci, drachmas.</hi> 6. <hi>Mineii ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi, drachmas</hi> 6. <hi>A ceti, drachmas,</hi> 3. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lei hemi.</hi> 2. conſequently when <hi>Galene</hi> had thus vſed it: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he came to <hi>ſicatri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiſes</hi> and for the outwarde parte he applyed <hi>Euphorbium</hi> mingled with Wax &amp; Roſin in forme of an Emplai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="cures">
               <pb facs="tcp:629:28"/>
               <head>Method for the curation of the wounds of <hi>Nerues</hi> or Sinewes and of what facultie the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cins which muſt be applyed ought tobe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Alen in his method of wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of <hi>Nerues,</hi> did vſe Liquid me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicins and ſometime Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſters. And without the wound about the place, hee applyed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoft Wul with hot Oile. Sometimes alſo he vſed Oil with a little Vinagre.<note place="margin">Vinagre is an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſinewes.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But in ſuch ſort that the colde vertue of the Vinagre was without offence, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe the ſuttlenes or perſing ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue did remain, and two or thrée times a day did vnbinde the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to ſee if the medicine did make any fretting in the Vlcer or ſore. And if it cauſed any greef or pain: then he fomented it with Oil as hot as the patient could indure.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">All colde things are contrary to the Nerues</note>For if it be but warme: it wil doo more hurt then good, and much worſe if it bee colde, for the colde dooth ſtop and hinder out breathing of the member. But the heate dooth reſolue and make thinner. &amp;c</p>
               <p>As for the vſe of water: it muſt bée in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:629:28"/> ſuch ſort vſed that at no time in the cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it touch y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Vlcer. Therfore when it dooth chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there remaineth any clut<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tered or congeled blood tobe taken away out of the wound: it muſt be doon w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Oil.</p>
               <p>And for an example: <hi>Galen</hi> reciteth an hiſtory of one which beeing hurt,<note place="margin">An hiſtory to prooue, that al cold is contrary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of Nerues.</note> was foure dayes without the féeling of anye pain, and when he did ſée that ther was no inflamation: he we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t abrode about cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tain erneſt buſines which he had to doo, the wether béeing very colde and taried ſomwhat long: then he returned to his houſe with great gréef and pain, euen to the very nape of his neck. Then <hi>Galen</hi> béeing called after that he did ſée the pain that the Patient was in: made fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with hot Oil all about the pained place, and applyed great quantitie of wul moiſtned in Oil, and the liquid me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicins made with <hi>Euphorbium</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtorum,</hi> and by this meanes the paine was eaſed, and after that he had ſlept: all the accidents did ceaſe.</p>
               <p>Therfore it is very profitable to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plye the Wul very warme, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinew it whether it be applyed with Oile, or Oile and Vinagre, which may wel be doon, if you apply alſo vpon it dry
<pb facs="tcp:629:29"/> Wul.</p>
               <p>And if it be in the Winter: the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent muſt keep his houſe vntill the fift or ſixth day of his greef. For if he be frée fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inflammation vntill the ſeuenth day, and that he feel no maner of pain or greef then he is without daunger.</p>
               <p>Alſo you ſhall kéep in memory that in this maner of cure, colde Oile &amp; aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent is contrary. But there muſt be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſuttleſt Oile that may be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, as very olde Oile, for lack of the medicine that is made of <hi>Euphorbium</hi> or Vinagre, or other ſuch proper medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine: <hi>Galen</hi> dooth teach to take in their rowme, <hi>Propolis</hi> beeing very new, li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quid and fat, and very olde Leuen, or els of the iuce of <hi>Tithimall,</hi> with newe Leuen, or <hi>Propolis</hi> liquified in Oile with Leuen, diſſolued in very ſharp Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagre, and the Oile muſt be very olde.</p>
               <p>The Floures that are tobe vſed to make <hi>Pultaſis</hi> or <hi>Cataplaſemus</hi> of:<note place="margin">The flours for to make Catapla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmus.</note> are <hi>Farina, Fabaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Orobi, id eſt erui Lolii. Ciceris vel Lupinorum, Amarorum polenta,</hi> made of Barly with <hi>Oximel,</hi> theſe <hi>Cataplaſmus</hi> bée not onely good in boiſterous people: but alſo to all others, whether there be any inflamation or no.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:629:29"/>
               <p>For lack of theſe aforeſaid medicins you may vſe theſe <hi>Cataplaſmus</hi> folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that is to ſay <hi>Propolis</hi> beeing new, <hi>Liquid</hi> and fat, and apply it vpon the wound, ſomtime with Leuen alone and ſomtimes with bothe, &amp; ſomtimes with mele of <hi>Orobis</hi> and Leuen, but the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen muſt be very olde, and contrarywiſe the <hi>Propolis</hi> muſt be new. If it be olde: you muſt ſoften it with Oile by the fire, or in the Sun, or els you may vſe the iuce of <hi>Tithimales</hi> mingled with Leuen or <hi>Oxelam,</hi> the Vinagre muſt be very ſharp wherwith the <hi>Oxelam</hi> is made.</p>
               <p>Theſe be medicens which may ſoon be had in a redines for lack of others,<note place="margin">Medicine which are eaſy tobe prepared.</note> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che at neceſſitie <hi>Galen</hi> did vſe in wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of <hi>Nerues.</hi> By this you ſhall note then that the medicins whiche be applyed in wounds of <hi>Nerues,</hi> in what maner ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be: ought tobe actually hot, and for the punctures or prickings of Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dones, the medicen which is made of <hi>Euphor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium</hi> and olde Oile, in the fourme of a <hi>Liquid cerat</hi> is very good and proper.</p>
               <p>And with the ſaid medicin <hi>Galen</hi> did heale one which was hurt in a tendone, within the ſpace of foure dayes.</p>
               <p>Then there was one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeeing the good
<pb facs="tcp:629:30"/> ſucceſſe that he had with the <hi>Euphorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> and Oile) thought to take an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by the ſaid curation, and did vſe new <hi>Euphorbium</hi> wherof did folowe greate heat and pain with corroſion in the Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer in ſo much that he was conſtrained to call <hi>Galene</hi> to remedy it, the whiche by fomentation of Oil and Vinagre did appeaſe the pain and diminiſh the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, wherfore it dooth appéer (as before hath been ſaid) that you muſt not neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to haue the knoweledge of the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and kindes of approoued medicins, and of them whiche wil ſoon looſe their ſtrength,<note place="margin">Note this wil.</note> from the others which doo kéep and maintain long time. For <hi>Euphor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Euphorbiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to knowe whether it be olde or new.</note> is one of theſe kindes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wil looſe his heat very ſoon, which is eaſy (by the coulour) tobe knowen. For if it be new: it is of an aſſhie couloure. But if it be olde: it is of a pale or yelowe colour, &amp; for that cauſe it is very dry, &amp; wil hardly be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in new Oil, for in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mingling it doth drink vp the Oile incontinent, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to diſſolue it wel:<note place="margin">The maner how to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue the Euphorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um and the nature and quality.</note> it muſt not be min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled togither with Oile all at one time, but laboured in a morter by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle for fear of running togithers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euphorbium</hi> is one of the Simples
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:629:30"/> which wil ſoon looſe his heate, and dooth not kéep long, which is knowen eaſely only by the colours without taſting of it.<note place="margin">Euphorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um is hot in the ii ij. degree.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Truely when it is olde, it is not of an Aſſhye coulour as it is when it is new, but it dooth decline toward a pale or ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowiſh colour, and if it be new: in the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of it, it will bee ſo hot that it wil burn the tung But if it be olde: you ſhall feel no great heate in it, neuertheleſſe, <hi>Euphorbiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> dooth keep his vertue longer then <hi>Tapſia,</hi> for <hi>Tapſia</hi> in i. yeer loſeth his ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth very much &amp; in ij. yeers loſeth his ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth vtterly &amp; is good for nothing. But <hi>Euphorbiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> if he be good when he is new, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay if he be hot &amp; burning as safore ſaid: he wil laſt thrée yéeres, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times foure yéeres &amp; to the fifth, but the he dooth vi. looſe all his force &amp; ſtrength.</p>
               <p>For whiche cauſe <hi>Galen</hi> did vſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times olde Oile without wax, for be cauſe that the <hi>Euphorbium</hi> was of fiue or ſix yéeres of age. So that the vſe of the <hi>Euphorbium</hi> cannot be comprehended by waight, for when it is new: ye muſt put twiſe ſo much Oile, and three times ſo much Wax, and if it be olde, the more Oile ſhalbe put to it and the leſſe Wax.</p>
               <p>Wherfore if you will make the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:629:31"/> medicament in fourme of a <hi>Liquid cerat:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The maner how to vſe the Euphor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bium whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be olde or new</note> you ſhall put foure times ſo muche Oile as Wax. But if you wil make it in fourme of a Plaiſter: you ſhall put therto as much Oile as Wax, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally if the Wax be olde and dry. For if the Wax be new: you ſhall not need ſo much Oile, and leſſe in Summer then in Winter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For to make Emplaſtrum Carotodes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is to ſay a Cerat or Ciroene, you ſhall take of the beſt wax, liquid it in Oile, then ad to the vi. parte of <hi>Euphor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium,</hi> and temper it, as aforeſaid, or els as foloweth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rec. Euphorbium, drachmas.</hi> 1. wax, <hi>drach.</hi> 6. Oile, <hi>drach.</hi> 5. or 6. And for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that the Wax is not ſo cleauing and viſcus as Roſin or Pitch is ye ſhall ad to either of the <hi>Cerats,</hi> Pich or Roſin,<note place="margin">The quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fferences of Roſins.</note> or of bothe, and then ye ſhall not need ſo much Oile as you ſhould haue doon, if it had been made onely with Wax. And this is to be noted that you ought to haue a diligent regarde to the moiſture or dry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of the Roſins, for you haue ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e more dryer then other ſome, and others again be more liquid. Of the dryeſt of theſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:629:31"/> kindes is that whiche ſome call <hi>Fricta,</hi> and others <hi>Colophonia.</hi> After the ſame kinde dooth folow, that which is brought in erthen pots, which is vnclarified, and when it is clarified: it is like the fore na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Fricta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is an other kinde which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Pityinon phiſema,</hi> that is to ſay <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man</hi> Pich which is more dryer then the other two aforſaid, the which <hi>Galen</hi> did iudge not tobe vſed in this cure becauſe of his vncleenes but did vſe the (afore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaid) <hi>Fricta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ther be diuers kindes of theſe (as before hath been ſaid) of the which ſome wil remain more liquid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other ſome,<note place="margin">The quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of Roſins ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their degres</note> for the Turpentine wil remain moſte liquid, the other dooth ſoon dry, as <hi>Stro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolina</hi> and <hi>Abiotina,</hi> and of theſe two, the hotteſt is <hi>Strobolina,</hi> and next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them in heat: is Turpentine.</p>
               <p>As for the Roſin of <hi>Cipres</hi> I doo not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, for <hi>Galene</hi> neuer durſt nor would vſe it in any Plaiſters to be applyed to <hi>Narues,</hi> becauſe it is aſtringant. The b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt and principall of all theſe kindes of Roſins: is Turpentine<note place="margin">The Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine is the moſte principall of all Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins.</note> not for his heat, for <hi>Strobolina</hi> and <hi>Abietina</hi> (as before hath been ſaid) are hotter.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:629:32"/>
               <p>The whiche Turpentine <hi>Galene</hi> did vſe by experiments, the great vtilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that was in it to mundify, to reſolue, and to drawe, and is very comfortable to the <hi>Nerues:</hi> witneſſes alſo therunto <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſcorides</hi> and <hi>Anabarzeus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when you wil haue the <hi>Cerat</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cleauing: you ſhall put to the more Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin (as is afore ſaid) and mix it according with the Oile and wax.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Emplaiſter which Galen did vſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>YOu ſhall take of Turpentine, and put therto thrée times ſo much wax. Then ad to them the xij. parte of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorbium,</hi> if you knowe not whether the <hi>Euphorbiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> be exactly hot or no: you muſt prooue when the medicine is made by this meanes, that is, ye ſhall ſtrike a little of it vpon a linnen cloth, and apply it vpon the thigh or arme, and there let it remain for a certain time, and if you perceiue that it dooth ſomewhat warme: then is the midicine temperat, and if it doo cauſe no maner of ſenſible heat,<note place="margin">Note this wel.</note> or els that he giue more feruent heat then he ought: it is certain y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the medicine is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to weke or to ſtrong. The heat may be diminiſhed by adding the more of Oyl
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:629:32"/> and wax, and alſo it may be augmented by adding to of the <hi>Euphorbium,</hi> for the confection of theſe kindes of medicins, the <hi>Propolis</hi> is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt and moſt conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g all other kindes of Roſins,<note place="margin">The vtility and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie of Propolis.</note> but it ought tobe new &amp; fat, becauſe it will the better drawe to the outwarde parte, the thick vapours, and ſuperfluous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, but Roſins are to be mingled with Wax, onely to giue thicknes and forme to plaiſters, and are not ſo conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable in this curatton as Propolis is.</p>
               <p>Therfore you ſhall note that in ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der &amp; ſoft complexions: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> medicins ought not tobe ſo ſtrong, as in ſtrong &amp; boiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous complections. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cerat which is mingled with olde Oile is very conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable in ſome, and likewiſe <hi>Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> that is to ſay Leuen, is very good ſo it be olde, for the older it is the better, be cauſe it dooth bothe reſolue and attract more then new, moreouer <hi>Sulphur Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uum</hi> is very good in theſe afore ſaid com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and it may be vſed with <hi>Tetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pharmacu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Alſo <hi>Aphronitrum</hi> may be vſed and <hi>Beronictum litrum,</hi> ſo that it be not grauely, which may alſo be min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with <hi>Tetrapharmacum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arſenicum</hi> wich is called in the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique
<pb facs="tcp:629:33"/> tung,<note place="margin">Quenched Lime.</note> 
                  <hi>Arenicum,</hi> beeing mingled with <hi>Tetrapharmacu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> is profitable, and for lack of theſe you ſhall vſe <hi>Sandaracha</hi> as of Lime quenched and vnquenched,<note place="margin">Metalla lo tione et aduſtione fuit miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ora.</note> waſhed &amp; vnwaſhed. But there muſt be leſſe of the vnwaſhed then of that which is waſhed: for becauſe that it is more ſharper then that which is vnwaſhed.</p>
               <p>Now then to haue the perfit knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to heale wounds of <hi>Nerues,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This ought to be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the cure of Nerues.</note> it is needful to knowe the end and intention of the cure, likewiſe the facultie of ſimple medicines the which in this cure ought to drawe and reſolue without exceſſiue heat and without great ſharpnes or by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. And likewiſe it is needful to know and vnderſtand perfectly the Anatho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye.<note place="margin">Note.</note> And the nature and complexion of the members of the body, and perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to vnderſtand and the difference betwéen the Tendones membranes &amp; ligamentꝭ for when occaſion ſhall ſerue to ſtich any wound: you muſt not touch the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dones, for the Tendones and the muſcles haue coniuncion togithers, therfore when the muſcles be ſeperated: there muſt be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good heed taken in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtitching of them, leſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou cauſe pain, for if they doo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure any pain: it cauſeth conuulſion, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:629:33"/> then afterwarde turneth to putrifaction, and ſo all the partes there abouts dooth ſuffer the like accidents, yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the muſculous fleſh may wel be ſtit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched as ſhalbe héerafter ſaid. Therfore to haue perfit knoweledge of the Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, this is to be vnderſtanded, that therbe two kindes: that is to ſay, the one round like vnto acorde, for which cauſe the ancient writers haue ſo called them: the others be flat like vnto membranes, wherof ſome paſſe along by the thighe néer vnto the knee. Alſo they are within the palmes of the hands and the ſoules of the feet.<note place="margin">Of tendo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ormes &amp; ſituations</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now we wil return to the matter, in wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of <hi>Nerues</hi> you muſt not make fomentation with hot water, as the Phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitions before <hi>Galenes</hi> time did: nor yet vſe <hi>Cataplaſmus</hi> made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wheat meal, and boyled with <hi>Hidrelaeum,</hi> for <hi>Galen</hi> made onely fomentation with Oile, and the medicines aforſaid, by which menes he healed many. And béeing but of the age of xxviij. yeeres, at whiche time hée came from <hi>Alexandrin</hi> into his owe con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey, did inuent and deuiſe the maner to cure the wounds of <hi>Nerues:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A note of Galen.</note> and ſince that time hath been many goodly cures,
<pb facs="tcp:629:34"/> by the method and midicines aforeſaid. And now for an example marke this hiſtory which is recited.</p>
               <p>Vpon a time (among others) there was a certain Captain af war, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che had a wound in his thigh, tranſuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſales, the whiche wound was of a great deapth, that the one ſide was drawen vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde &amp; the other downwarde towarde the knée, &amp; for to heale the ſaid wound: <hi>Galen</hi> did not dout to ſtich it in the muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous partes. Neuertheleſſe he gaue good reſpect in touching of any Tendon, for he knew that the muſcles might wel be ſtitched without daunger and not the tendones, albeit that ſome ancient Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions doo ſtich but onely the vpper lips of the ſkin, though the wound be neuer ſo deep, for they did fear to ſtich y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> muſcles, and there were others whiche would ſtich the fleſhey parts of the muſcles, but they were of the vpper parte of the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and not in the depth.</p>
               <p>Wherfore when there did chaunce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny déep wound béeing tranſuerſales: he did boldely ſtitch the muſculous partes. As for the other woundꝭ made according to the length of the member: it is not néedful to ſtitch them, for with good and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:629:34"/> conuenient rowling the muſculous parts may wel be agglutinated.</p>
               <p>Therfore they which be ignorant in the Anothomy, doo fear to ſtich the mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>branes with the muſcles, but <hi>Galen</hi> bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing learned in that matter, did ſtiche them ſafely &amp; without danger, although that the large Tendones are muche like the membranes, yet for all that, there is difference, for the Tendones be more hard and of a grocer ſubſtance, then the ſaid membranes be.<note place="margin">The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwen the tendo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes.</note> Except it be in the muſcles of <hi>Abdomen,</hi> which the Prince <hi>Auicenna</hi> calleth <hi>Mirac,</hi> for in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> place they be very tender and ſuttle, as the membranes be in all points, except it be in the ſtraight muſcles.</p>
               <p>By this it appéereth that the iij parte of Phiſick which the gréeks call <hi>Chirurgia</hi> that is to ſay, the which is exerciſed by handy operation. <hi>Pharmaceutice,</hi> that is to ſay by medicines as to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Apothecary. Diaitetice,</hi> by regiment of the life, haue néed one of the other: wherfore he whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che dooth take vpon him this profeſſion: ought exactly to be exerciſed in theſe iij.<note place="margin">Note this place wel.</note>
               </p>
               <p>After that he firſt hath had the perfet knoweledge of the <hi>Theorick,</hi> that is to ſay ſpeculatiue, in the whiche is taught
<pb facs="tcp:629:35"/> the method to cure by reaſons and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations, and if he be ignorant in a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny of theſe: he is not worthy to be called a good Chirurgion, and ſhall neuer be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to doo any thing, which ſhalbe to the profit or eaſement of his Patients.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The compoſition of medicines for wounds of the Nerues made of metalles.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt the metalls you muſt auoid them which are aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, and principally in the prickings of the Sinewes.<note place="margin">The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of metalls.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But the abſterſiues, as <hi>Aeris ſquama,</hi> &amp; others are profitable. And this muſt be noted y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all metalls are partly of a groce and terrene ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, becauſe that there dooth contain in them, much earthy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wherfore they doo require to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, to the end that they may be more ſuttle. One way to prepare them is this.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">To prepare the metals.</note>Firſt the ſaid metalls ought to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured in a morter, onely with very ſtrong Vinagre, which hath a pearcing facultie, and ought to be ſo laboured ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry long.</p>
               <p>Ther be ſome of the ſaid metalls that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:629:35"/> wil not wel be beaten, although they be very long labored. Neuertheleſſe they may eaſely be diſſolued as <hi>Chalcitis, mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſy</hi> and ſuch like, but others may be bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and reduſed into poulder, as <hi>Aeris Squama</hi> and ſuch others. And this you ſhall note, that <hi>Chalcitis</hi> &amp; <hi>Erugo</hi> if they be burnt: they haue leſſe ſharpnes in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherfore the greater quantitie may be occupyed when any medicine is made.</p>
               <p>The Paſtils or <hi>Trocis</hi> of <hi>Andronis Poluidas</hi> and <hi>Pacion,</hi> be right excellent and conueniable in wounds of Sinews, ſo that they be diſſolued in <hi>Sapa</hi> as they ought.<note place="margin">Excellent paſtils.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sapa</hi> is made of <hi>Muſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sapa and wherof it is made.</note> that is to ſay ſodden <hi>Wine,</hi> but the ſaid <hi>Muſt</hi> ought to be made of ſwéet Rayſons, and not of ſower, which are Abſterſiues and of the latter running of the Tub, the whiche wine muſt be boyled vnto the conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the half, and with the ſaid Wine the Paſtils may be diſſolued, to be apply<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed vnto the <hi>Nerues</hi> which lye bare. But when you vſe them, you ſhall take that kinde of <hi>Polidas,</hi> for they be moſte tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, and principally in theſe bodyes which are temperate &amp; tender, in which bodyes all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kindes of Paſtils ought not
<pb facs="tcp:629:36"/> tobe vſed, but medicins according, which we haue al redy ſpoken of, and wil ſpeak héerafter, for all bodies be not of one tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perature, for they differ in thrée things, that is to ſay, as for their temperature, ſecondly in the augmentation of their age, and laſt in their ſtates and exerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as they whiche woork much, or liue idlely. Wherfore it foloweth that no medicine can bee conuenient,<note place="margin">A method worthy to be noted.</note> in all bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes. And for this cauſe you muſt haue two ſortes of medicines, the one ſtrong: and the other weke, and then when ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie dooth require,<note place="margin">According to the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature of the body y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> midicine ought to be compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plyed.</note> the mixtures may be according to the temperature of the body.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Medicins for ſtrong and boiſterous people.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rec. Aeris ſquama parte.</hi> 3. <hi>Miſyos crudi partes.</hi> 2. <hi>Chalciteos cruda parte</hi> 1. <hi>Cerae parte.</hi> 12. At the beginning when <hi>Galene</hi> prepared this medicament: hée did put to it <hi>Arſenicon,</hi> and after that when he ſawe that it was ſuperfluous: he left it out.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Medicine for delicate and tender complexions.</head>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:629:36"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rec. Miſyos combuſti, Chalcitidis vſti ana, parte,</hi> 1. <hi>Aeris ſquamae partes.</hi> 4. <hi>Cerae, parte,</hi> 18.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Medicin for mean complectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s whiche Galen</hi> did often vſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rec. Miſyos vſti. Chalcities vſtae, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rugini vſtae ana, parte,</hi> 1. <hi>Aeris ſquamae part,</hi> 3. <hi>Cerae, part.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>For to make theſe medicines, the quantitie of the Oile ought to exceed the quantitie of the Wax,<note place="margin">Note that Galenes pound is but xii. vnces.</note> as if there be viij. vnces of Wax, you ſhall put xij. vnces of Oile (which is a pound) and the Oile muſt be like the Oile of <hi>Sauen,</hi> that is to ſay, of a ſuttle ſubſtance, and not aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, and the olde Oile is beſt. Where<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore new Oil which the Greeks call <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>motribes,</hi> is neither good nor conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</p>
                  <p>After that the metalles haue béene wel beaten long time with Vinagre: you ſhall ad to of <hi>Thus,</hi> but it muſt be white and good, then again you ſhall beat it with the metalls, before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you ad to the <hi>Cerot,</hi> but the quantitie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Thus</hi> ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be the half of the medicins, for to make the medicine in a meane temperature. And if you wil make it more weak: you
<pb facs="tcp:629:37"/> ſhall ad to more then the half of <hi>Thus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And if you wil haue the medicin more ſharper: you ſhall not put to the halfe of <hi>Thus</hi> in the forſaid medicine. It is expe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dient that ye mingle ſome Roſin w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Wax and Oil, neuertheleſſe you ought to conſider, that if you doo put to it <hi>Stro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolina,</hi> that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> medicin wilbe more ſtron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger and ſharper, and if you put to it of <hi>Terebenthine:</hi> the medicin wilbe more ſofter and meane in ſharpnes, and if you wil haue it betwéen bothe: you ſhall put to it <hi>Abietine</hi> or <hi>Beniamin larix,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litie of Larix.</note> which is one of the moiſteſt Roſins, and is of ſubſtance like vnto liquid Pich, whiche ſome merchants and Factors ſel for <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebenthine,</hi> to them that knowe it not, nor can diſcerne the one from the other.</p>
                  <p>Yet not withſtanding there is great difference which may be eaſely kowen by the taſte and by the ſharp ſmel which he hath more then <hi>Terebenthine,</hi> neuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theleſſe their ſtrength dooth not differ much.</p>
                  <p>Wherfore if you wil make your medi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cine in forme of an Emplaſter: you ſhall mingle with your Wax, the vi. parte of the ſaid Roſin, which is for a pound of wax: ij. vnces of Roſin, and if it be liquid
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:629:37"/> and fat, half an vnce ſhall ſuffiſe. And when you wil not make the medicin in forme of an implaiſter: you may leaue out the ſaid Roſin, but you may ad to of <hi>Galbanum</hi> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times aſmuch as of <hi>Thus</hi> according as need dooth require. For when you put to aſmuch <hi>Galbanum</hi> as <hi>Thus:</hi> the medicament is the gentiller, and when you will haue it more ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: you ſhall put to it but half ſo muche <hi>Galbanum,</hi> and ſometimes the leſſer waight or quantitie, as if there be iiij. <hi>dragmes</hi> of <hi>Thus,</hi> and iiij. <hi>drams</hi> of <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>banum:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">This is ment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Galbanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid then the Thus.</note> the medicine ſhalbe the more mitigatiue and gentle. But if you put to but ij. <hi>drams</hi> of <hi>Galbanum:</hi> the medicine wilbe ſomewhat ſtronger. Wherfore in ſenſible and tender bodyes or <hi>Caco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chime</hi> it is expedient to haue the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine tobe prepared with the more quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of <hi>Galbanum.</hi> Then when you wil make your medicine tobe applyed to the <hi>Nerue</hi> béeing bare or diſcouered: you ſhall not put in ſo much <hi>Galbanum</hi> for fear of cauſing pain, for the Sinews béeing bare may not abide any ſtrong medicine.</p>
                  <p>Among the ſimples, Vinagre is ſharp and very painful, and for that cauſe Oil
<pb facs="tcp:629:38"/> is applyed with it, and alſo ſometimes <hi>Galbanum,</hi> and for lack of <hi>Galbanum:</hi> you may take ſuch greaces that are of fine &amp; ſuttle ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as of wilde beaſts, that is to ſay, of Lions, wilde Bores, Leopards or Beares.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe of flying foules, as of wilde Ducks and ſuch other like,<note place="margin">The choiſe of the beſt greaces.</note> in their ſted you may take of Cocks, Hennes or Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, but this is tobe noted that the grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of wilde flying fowles and whiche doo liue abrode in the feelds,<note place="margin">Note this for they which doo not exerciſe the body doth engen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der humorꝭ groce and colde and vndiſgeſted</note> are better then of them which be nouriſhed about the houſes, for thoſe which be nouriſhed within or about any houſes: are more heauy, and their fat is of a more groſe ſubſtance and more moiſt, for becauſe that they are ſhut vp, &amp; haue no ſcope to flye or run as the others doo, for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe &amp; ſtirring of their bodyes dooth ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and make fine their groſe humours.</p>
                  <p>When you wil haue your medicin of the thicknes of a <hi>Cerot:</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the third or fourth parte of Wax, or if the greace be very moiſt: you may put to the one half of Wax, and ſo after ſuch ſort as ſhalbe thought good, but if the greace be mene between bothe, that is to ſay neither to dry nor to moiſt: you
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:629:38"/> ſhall ad to the third part of wax, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che <hi>Cerot</hi> ſhalbe proffitable for many purpoſes, and is called <hi>Diaſteaton,</hi> that is to ſay made with Talow and greace.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ The Medicine which is called Dieuphorbium.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E haue ſpoken héertofore of the qualitie, nature and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie of the <hi>Euphorbium,</hi> and after what ſorte it wil keep, &amp; how in time he looſeth his ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth and how he muſt be knowen by his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Now we wil intreat of the medicines whiche are compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the ſaid <hi>Euphorbium,</hi> and is made as foloweth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rec. Euphorbii, parte,</hi> 1. <hi>Cerae partes</hi> 3. <hi>Olei, partes,</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>To the compoſition of this medicine the wax ought tobe triple, that is to ſay, iij. times ſo much in reſpect as of the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorbium</hi> and the Oile the fourth part, but the <hi>Euphorbium</hi> muſt be new and good. The vſe of this medicine is profita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble in the punctures of <hi>Nerues,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The vertue of this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine.</note> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when it is feared y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d wil cloſe vp, therfore it is neceſſary to haue a
<pb facs="tcp:629:39"/> reſpect to the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gh of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> medicin, for if it be to weke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tity of <hi>Euphorbiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> may be augmented, ſomtimes there may be added to the half of <hi>Euphorbium,</hi> &amp; ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times aſmuch as of wax or more. Name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly if the <hi>Euphorbiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> be olde, for it muſt be according to the ſtrength of the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. But if the medicine be to ſtrong: you may weaken it by adding to of ſome Oil, or els to make an other more wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker according to the forme and maner a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>foreſaid. And if you wil knowe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the medicine is to ſtrong: you ſhall marke theſe ſignes that folow, that is to wit, if the Patient féeleth great heat with <hi>Ero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Signes for to knowe whether that the me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicine be to ſtrong.</note> or if the partes about it be hotter then they were before, or if the pricking pain bee more raiſed vp then it ought to be, or if the ſide of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid prick haue any inflamation.</p>
                  <p>Therfore for to chuſe apt and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient medicins: it is needful to make the compoſition in the which there is put iij. times ſo much wax as new <hi>Euphorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> the whiche is more ſtronger then the other. If there be v. times ſo muche Wax: the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſition ſhalbe more weke and gentle. And if there be iiij. times ſo much wax: the compoſition ſhalbe mene
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:629:39"/> betwéen bothe. And if you wil haue your Vnguents ſuch as the Phiſitions call <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>copa,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Without labour. Vnguentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Acopa.</note> that is to ſay taking away of we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines or pain: you ſhall put to iiij. times ſo much Oile as Wax. But if you wil haue it in forme of a liquid <hi>Cerot:</hi> you ſhall put to double of Oile to the Wax and if the Wax be dry: you ſhall put to of Oile ij. partes and a half, whiche is to ſay, for one pound of Wax, ij. pound and a half of Oile. And if you wil make it plaiſter wiſe: there muſt be added as much Wax as Oil, namely if the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be temperat. And if the wax be to olde and dry, and that the weather be colde: there muſt be ſomwhat more Oil then wax. But if the wax be new and moiſt, and the weather hot: there muſt be ſomwhat more Wax then Oile, that is to ſay, for one pound of wax: xiij. vnces of Oile, &amp; in the compoſition of the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, for the better mingling of the Oile and Wax togither: you ſhall ad to ſome Roſin and principally of <hi>Terebenthine</hi> or in ſted <hi>Colophonia,</hi> and if you doo ad aſmuch of it as of Wax: the Pich dooth make the conſiſtance of the <hi>Cerot,</hi> and note, that which is moſte liquideſt: is the beſt, euen in like ſorte as of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins.
<pb facs="tcp:629:40"/> And if the Roſin be liquid, as is the new <hi>Terebenthine:</hi> it ſhall ſuffiſe to put in the third parte, in reſpect of the Wax.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Galen</hi> did compound any me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, wherin is Roſin and wax, it is to be vnderſtanded that hee ment not that which was dry and olde: but ſuch kindes of Roſin and Wax that were of a ment ſubſtance, for els béeing mingled with the others wil ſoone dry and looſe their ſtrength, and that for two cauſes. The firſt by the intemperature of heat of the weather, and ſecondly by the reaſon of béeing to long kept. As for Propolis: it is no other thing but white Wax, and it is more conueniable in plaiſters and <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rots</hi> then Roſin or Pitch. And more <hi>Galene</hi> dooth account <hi>Terebenthine</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Roſins, and is moſte conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of all the Roſins in the fore ſaid plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and <hi>Cerots.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Medicines made of Simples whiche wil diſſolue.</head>
                  <p>THeſe Simples which folowe are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quible, that is to ſay, which wil di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſolue vpon the fire, and whereof <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rots</hi> and Plaiſters be made, and may
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:629:40"/> be boiled with moiſt things as with wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, Wine and Vinagre.</p>
                  <p>The ſimples, which are theſe that fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, Propolis, Wax, Roſin, <hi>Ladanum</hi> and <hi>Senum,</hi> that is to ſay, Talowe, and <hi>Galbanum,</hi> whiche muſt be prepared in a double veſſel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly called <hi>Balneum Mariae,</hi> whiche is aſmuch to ſay, in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the foreſaid ſimples within ſome veſſel, and then to ſet it in a Cauldron of water vpon the fire. There are alſo ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wil aſwel diſſolue without fire as with fire, in moiſt things as <hi>Gutta Am<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moniaci,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> licour of <hi>Sagapeni, Panacis, Cerapion</hi> and <hi>Oppoponax.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rec. Oppoponacis, Galbani, Tere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benthine, Propolis, ana parte.</hi> 1</p>
                  <p>You ought to take good héed tbat your <hi>Propolis</hi> be neither dry nor olde, but for lack of the other: you may put in ſuch as may be gotten, but it muſt be double in waight and the other Simples muſt be new and liquid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Another of the ſame effect.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rec. Aſeti ſexta</hi> 1. <hi>Picis.</hi> 1, pound. <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poponacis</hi> 4. vnces, the Pitch muſt be boyled with the Vinagre. <hi>Et fiat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:629:41"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The vſe and facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit of theſe medicines.</note>Theſe medicins afore named are good in punctures of <hi>Nerues,</hi> and for biting of mad Dogs, and principally for a wound made by any venemous beaſt, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that they are percing, and doo kéep the ſides of the wound from ſhutting togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the whiche meanes the venim which lyeth within: ſhall the more eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be drawen out. But for becauſe that the ſaid medicines are ſtrong: you muſt vſe them in ſtrong &amp; boiſterous bodyes.</p>
                  <p>And if the ſaid diſeaſes, doo chaunce in tender and delicate people, as wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and little Children: then they muſt be liquifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſome kinde of Oil, or reſolutiue Vnguent, namely <hi>Amaricum</hi> and <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pobalſamum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then afterwards with <hi>Irinum</hi> and <hi>Comagenum,</hi> and in ſted of theſe <hi>Suſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> and <hi>Ciprinum,</hi> or if theſe be not to be had: you ſhall take Oil. Or if it be in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> you ſhall take <hi>Oleum reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> and <hi>Rhaphaninum,</hi> for ſurely there is abundance of this aforeſaid in <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> &amp; alſo through all <hi>Egipt.</hi> But there is not tobe found <hi>Oleum ſinapinum</hi> but with great diſicultie, the which Oile if it be put in the afore ſaid medicament: there is no dout but that it will be much more
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:629:41"/> ſtronger and better to kéep open the pun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctures of the <hi>Nerues,</hi> and if you haue no <hi>Oppoponax</hi> to make the ſaid medicin withall: you may take <hi>Sagapenum</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued in Vinagre, Roſin or <hi>Propolis,</hi> or ſome greaces,<note place="margin">The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which are moſte requiſite in this medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine.</note> béeing very olde ſo that they be ſharp, and of a ſuttle ſubſtance, as of a Lyon, Leopard, Beare or Fox or els of wilde Ducks.</p>
                  <p>Or els theſe greaces folowing béeing very olde, of a Bul or of a Gote. And this is to be noted, that the older the greaces be: the more ſharper, and namely the greace of a Hog the whiche is more ſoft and moiſt then all the aforeſaid. And of the like nature is Wine and Vinagre and Mary, but of all Maryes: the beſt is the mary of a Hart, or of a Calf. Of theſe aforeſaid medicines <hi>Galene</hi> dooth coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſail to haue in a redineſſe, the whiche he did alwaies vſe in punctures of <hi>Nerues,</hi> wherwith he had good ſucceſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The vſe of Pigeons dung.</head>
                  <p>FOr becauſe that Pigions dung is ſharp: it muſt be vſed in the ſtead of <hi>Euphorbium,</hi> neuertheleſſe it is of a more ſuttle ſubſtance the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Euphorbium,</hi> wherfore it is more conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in ſtrong
<pb facs="tcp:629:42"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:629:42"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:629:43"/> and boiſterous people, as ruſticall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes dryed with labours, <hi>Galen</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times did mingle metalls togithers bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Vinagre in the forme (as before hath béen ſaid) and by that meanes the medicine was made more ſharp, euen as though he had put in Verdegrece.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of Medicines called Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botanum, that is to ſay, made of herbes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Alen the interpreter of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick and lerned in all thingꝭ: would omit nothing whiche did appertain to the curation of wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of <hi>Nerues,</hi> for whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che cauſe he hath taught diuers maners of curations, to the end that if the one ſhould faile: they ſhould haue others at all times when néed required, and alſo when vpon the ſuddaine a Chirurgian is called to viſit any Patients, wheras the Simples requiſit cannot be gotten, therfore <hi>Galen</hi> right wiſely hath taught the way to compou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d medicins for wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of <hi>Nerues</hi> with hearbes in ſtead of the mettalls aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Firſt the ſaid <hi>Galen</hi> did compound
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:629:43"/> medicines for wounded <hi>Nerues</hi> of thoſe herbes which were of a ſuttle ſubſtance,<note place="margin">Herbs and roots for the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of medicines.</note> that is to wit of <hi>Dictamus, Amaracus,</hi> and <hi>Malus terrae</hi> whiche is <hi>Ariſtolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiae,</hi> moreouer he did make ſome in the which he did put in <hi>Marou amaricum,</hi> which is <hi>Margerum, Polium argemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae,</hi> whiche is called <hi>Aigrimony, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mapitis id eſt vina artetica centaurium Radicis omnium, Ariſtolochiarum, Draconculi, Ficus agreſtis, Brionia, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thea, Iridis, Acori mei, Aſari phoud eſt Valeriana, Gentiana</hi> and <hi>Panacis.</hi> All the which herbes and roots afore named <hi>Galen</hi> hath written and declared in his Books of Simples. And this you ſhall note, that becauſe they haue a bitteriſh taſt without abſterſion or immoderate ſharpnes: they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient in woundꝭ of <hi>Nerues,</hi> and how they ought tobe vſed marke this that foloweth.<note place="margin">The maner for to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicins with the ſaid herbes.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt they muſt be dryed, then ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and beaten very fine, then ſearced through a fine ſearce. For if it be of a groce ſubſtance: it is not conuenient in wounds of <hi>Nerues,</hi> which dooth require the moſte ſuttle and fineſt that may be, (as before hath béen ſaid) then after that theſe hearbes and Rootes be finely pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred:
<pb facs="tcp:629:44"/> they muſt be mingled with Wax and Oyle, in ſuche ſort as we haue ſaid of <hi>Euphorbium.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Compoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of the Nerues, which the Greeks call Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liteleis, that is to ſay ſumpteous,</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not onely profitable to haue the knowledge to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound medicins of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples aforeſaid: but others ſumpteous &amp; of great price, for although y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be but ſeldom vſed, yet neuertheleſſe it fortuneth ſomtimes, that if you haue a great number of medi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cines: you ſhal ſcant pleaſe the Patient, for he wil haue them made of ſuch Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples as are very ſumptuous. As for an example <hi>Galen</hi> maketh mention of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rich man whiche he dooth not name, in his firſt Book of the knowledge of the iudgement of the pulſe, and this third Book. The which rich man did by all the menes poſſible he could, approoue to heale a maligne Vlcer vpon one of his ſeruants, then when he did ſée that he could not heale it: he did commit it into <hi>Galens</hi> hands, and after that he percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:629:44"/> that <hi>Galen</hi>
                  <note place="margin">An hiſtory of a cure which Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len did on a maligne Vlcer.</note> had healed it: he did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him to giue him the receipt of the midicine wherwith he did heal his fore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaid ſeruant. The ſaid rich man did not conſider that there are many kindes of maligne Vlcers: but thought with one medicine to heale all maner of vlcers, yet neuertheleſſe <hi>Galen</hi> did giue to him the foreſaid receipt. But when he had the compoſition: he ſaid go thy waies and giue thy receipt to beggers, and let me haue an other more coſtlyer and of richer Simples.</p>
               <p>And alſo at a nother time when hée could not heale a Childe that had a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain infirmitie about his eare (with his owne medicine whiche he vſed without method) did ſend him to <hi>Galen,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards he met with one by chaunce, of whome hee did vnderſtand that the ſaid Childe was healed: he was very deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to knowe what maner of medicin <hi>Galen</hi> vſed.</p>
               <p>Then conſidering that he had ſéen ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny that haue béen wounded, bothe in <hi>Nerues</hi> and other places, and hauing their fingers cut with putrifaction, and ſome of them haue dyed, and others la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. And contrary wiſe he did vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb facs="tcp:629:45"/> that none of them whiche <hi>Galene</hi> did dreſſe dyed, nor were in daunger of death, but that ſpéedyly did help them: he demaunded the receipt of ſame maner of ſumptuous or odorifferous Vnguent for wounds of <hi>Nerues,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">An excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t method to cure wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of Nerues.</note> then <hi>Galene</hi> did giue to him many receipts faithfully diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>penſed, with the whiche hee healed ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny that had wounds in the <hi>Nerues,</hi> for the which he gaue <hi>Galen</hi> great prayſe, and gaue him moſte harty thanks for gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo liberally, for whiche cauſe he did preſent <hi>Galen</hi> with a preſent, the receipts which he gaue him were theſe that folow.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rec. Cinamomi, Dictamni, Mary, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na drach.</hi> 40.</p>
               <p>Certainly theſe Simples are odori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fferous and ſuttle, hee would not put in <hi>Amaracum,</hi> becauſe it had not a good ſmel, alſo at <hi>Rome</hi> it was very hard to be found, as of <hi>Marum.</hi> You muſt beat theſe Simples very fine and ſerce them as before hath béen ſaid, and then tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per them with the <hi>Cerot</hi> made of very good <hi>Oppobalſame,</hi> and <hi>Tyrrhenique</hi> Wax, which <hi>Cerot</hi> is made of viij. parts of Wax, and x. parts of <hi>Oppobalſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:629:45"/>
                  <head>¶ The compoſition of the receipt is thus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rec. Cerae, parte.</hi> 8. <hi>Oppobalſame, parter.</hi> 10. ad to of the beſt Turpentine <hi>parte</hi> 1. the <hi>Terebenthine</hi> is added to in the end, and if you wil haue the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine cleauing, and of a reſonable forme: you may ad to alſo of precious <hi>Mirrh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Where the <hi>Nerues</hi> were bare <hi>Galen</hi> did vſe the <hi>Cerot</hi> which the Gréeks call <hi>Mirepſice,</hi> &amp; the Vnguents<note place="margin">The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pare Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guents.</note> whiche the <hi>Romains</hi> call <hi>Vnguentum ſpicatum,</hi> and <hi>Phuliatum,</hi> in adding to the xij. part of <hi>Pompholigoes</hi> waſhed, which muſt be prepared with <hi>Terrhenique,</hi> Wax, and burnt <hi>Nardus</hi> in a double veſſell, which is vulgarly called <hi>Balneum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae,</hi> and all Vnguents ought tobe prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after the like ſorte.</p>
                  <p>In punctures of <hi>Nerues</hi> the moſte ſharpeſt medicines are moſte conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent becauſe they kéep the wound open, but in wounds of nerues diſcouered,<note place="margin">A note of punctures and wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of Nerues diſcouered.</note> it is conuenient to vſe medicines whiche haue a mene aſtrictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with reſolute ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and without biting, as <hi>Amomum. ſpicanardi,</hi> and <hi>Folium Malabathri.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:629:46"/>
               <head>The compoſition of Medicines by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Phiſitions which Galen ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mention of.</head>
               <p>THere was none before <hi>Galens</hi> time which did write the reaſon and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner to cure the wounds of <hi>Nerues,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe ſome haue ſince his time, but without diſtinction and good order. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other a Phiſition of his time did prepare one as foloweth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rec. Cerae.</hi> 6, vnces. <hi>Olei.</hi> vnces. 9. <hi>Myſeos.</hi> vnces. 6. <hi>Chalcitidis. drach.</hi> 1. <hi>Aeris ſquama.</hi> vnces 2. and a half. <hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> half an vnce. <hi>Galbani</hi> 1. vnce.</p>
               <p>The Simples which may be liqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, that is to ſay, the Wax and the <hi>Galbanum</hi> after that they be reſolued: you ſhall mix them with the mettalls. firſt béeing beaten very fine with ſtrong Vinagre. <hi>Galene</hi> neuer knew the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this compoſition, and ſaith that he neuer found it neither in <hi>Aſclepia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Apothecary,</hi> nor in <hi>Petron,</hi> nor in <hi>Andromacus.</hi> Albeit that the ancient Phiſitions did compound good medicins.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:629:46"/>
                  <head>Another of Adromachus.</head>
                  <p>The whiche is good as <hi>Aſclepiades</hi> dooth write for wounds in <hi>Nerues</hi> and Muſcles, contuſions and gallings, and for any member béeing broken, there may be made with it alſo <hi>Collires,</hi> for diſeaſes of the eyes, and is a good reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye for pain of the hed and for all greefs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rec, Argenti ſpuma,<note place="margin">Alius. 18</note> Cerae ana drach</hi> 144 <hi>Ammoniaci drach.</hi> 72. <hi>Tereben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thine drach.</hi> 36. <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oe ſuccidae com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtae drach.</hi> 12. <hi>Aeris ſquamme, Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, Ariſtolochiae ana drach,</hi> 8. <hi>Olei ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cini hemi.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p>The maner to prepare it is thus. Firſt you ſhall boil the Oile and the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>targe</hi> togither, af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er that ad to the Wax and the Turpentine, and when it hath boyled till it come to a reſonable conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: you ſhall ad to <hi>Ammoniacum.</hi> Note that this medicine<note place="margin">The facul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of this medicine.</note> is not conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in punctures of <hi>Nerues:</hi> for becauſe it is aſtringant. Neuertheleſſe it may be vſed where the <hi>Nerues</hi> and tendones be diſcouered. And if there be any infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: it muſt be liquified with Oile of Roſes, and if there be none: it may be liquified with olde Oil, <hi>Recinum cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mamelium</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:629:47"/> and others which are for ſoft and tender bodyes, and for the ſtrong and boiſterous: you ſhall vſe ſtrong Oile as <hi>Oleum radicis, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>icus, Aggreſtis, Bri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oniae, Aſari, Dracunculi, Ariſtolochiae</hi> and <hi>Panacis,</hi> but the <hi>Ariſtolochia</hi> and <hi>Panacis</hi> ar more ſtrong then the others.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another compoſed by Clau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dius Philoxenus Chirurgion for the foreſaid greefs.</head>
                  <p>Rec. Argenti ſpumae, Cerae ana drach 160. Ammoniaci, drach. 80. Propoleos drach 40.<note place="margin">Alius. 18.</note> Terebenthine, Reſine, Siccae, Thuris, Squame aeris, ana drach. 16. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae ſuccide<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>buſtae, Squamae Stomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matis, ana, drach. 8. Oppoponacis dra. 4. Olei ricini hemi. 3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A reddish medicine of <hi>Halieus.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rec. Argenti ſpumae, Cerae ana. drach</hi> 100,<note place="margin">Alius. 100</note> 
                     <hi>Terebenthinae, Mannae, Thuris, Galbani, Minii Cinoptici, ana drach.</hi> 8 <hi>Olei ſexta.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>This implaiſter<note place="margin">The vtilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this Emplaiſter</note> is good in gréene wounds, and for wounds of the <hi>Nerues,</hi> and for Vlcers of the eyes, whiche bee hard to cicatrice. And to reſolue all hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:629:47"/> and principally of the Dugs. It is likewiſe good for biting of mad Dogs, and for the ſtinging of Dragons, and the venimouſe fiſh called in Greek <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon Thalaſſia,</hi> and in Latin <hi>Paſtinaca Marina, Aſclepiades</hi> dooth write that it is onely for wounds, &amp; maketh no menti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on for punctures of <hi>Nerues</hi> although it wil ſerue in bothe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another catagmatique me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicin compoſed by Moſchion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rec. Argenti ſpumae, minam.</hi> 1. which is 160. <hi>drach. Picis aride drach.</hi> 160, <hi>Seue vitulinae dra.</hi> 160. <hi>Reſine Terebenthine drach.</hi> 80. <hi>Manne thuris drach.</hi> 80. <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae drach.</hi> 40. <hi>Eruginis oppoponacis, Galbani ana drach</hi> 8. <hi>Olei ricini hemi</hi> 1. <hi>Aceti hemi.</hi> 1. <hi>Licorice cicamini he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi,</hi> 1. <hi>Picis liquid, ciath.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p>The manner to boil this Vnguent is thus. Firſt you ſhall boile the <hi>Litarge</hi> and the Oile togither, then ad to the Calues greace, and after that the <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> and the <hi>Thuris,</hi> let them be ſtirred continually til they be incorporated, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſhall put to it the Pich, the wax and the Turpentine, and conſequently the others, which muſt be boyled in fourme
<pb facs="tcp:629:48"/> of an Emplaiſter, after that you ſhall ad to the <hi>Galbanum, Eruge</hi> and <hi>Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponax,</hi> diſſolued in Vinagre, then ye ſhall take the licour of <hi>Cicamini,</hi> and the liquid Pich, and boil them in another veſſel, and when they bee melted togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſomwhat thick: you ſhall min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle them with the others, and ſet them on the fire again, til they come to a per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fit conſiſtance.</p>
                  <p>Then you ſhall let it ſtepe in white Wine the ſpace of iij. dayes, after you may ſtrike it vpon a linnen cloth to vſe as an Emplaiſter.</p>
                  <p>This Emplaiſter<note place="margin">The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of this Emplaiſter</note> is very good in gréen wounds, and for cutting and contuſion of <hi>Nerues,</hi> for a Fracture with a wound and with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient ligature dooth cauſe calles to ingender in bones, it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe good in the beginning of an Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dropſye, for contufion of the Teſticles, for <hi>Rhagadies,</hi> for Tumours of the Throte called of the greeks, <hi>Bron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chocilas,</hi> to be bréef this is a right excellent medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:629:48"/>
            <head>¶ The curation of wounds of Nerues, Tendons &amp; ioints,</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He cauſe of ſolu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion</hi> of continuitie the whole and ſound partes in <hi>Nerueus</hi> places, may chaunce diuers waies, that is to ſay, by contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, as blowes with Stones, Staues, Hammers, Clubs, Hargubuſh, Croſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowes, bitings and ſuch other like. Like<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe it may come by ſharp and pricking Inſtruments. As a Bodkin, Speare, Dart, Thorne or venimouſe Beaſt, or ſuch like. Alſo by cutting with a ſwoord, or Knife. Of the which wounds ſome be made acording to the length of the Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, <hi>Nerue</hi> or Sinew, Membrane or Caule, and others according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bredth with great inciſion, and ſome meane or leſſer, of the which hurts theſe accidentꝭ may folow.</p>
            <p>As pain, vehement fluxion, inflama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Feuer, loſſe of reaſon, <hi>Sinope,</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtume, <hi>Gangrena,</hi> and mortification of the whole parte, and ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times death by reaſon of the communication and
<pb facs="tcp:629:49"/> conſent that they haue with the Brain and other noble partes.</p>
            <p>Moreouer it is to bee vnderſtanded, that when the <hi>Nerues</hi> or Tendones bee but half or little cut, the wound is more daungerous, then if they were cut quite a ſunder.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">That whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch couereth the Scul.</note>And ſo is it with the <hi>Perioſten, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricranium</hi> and membranes, or becauſe that the portion or parte that is cut doth drawe him ſelf to his beginning, which cauſeth conuultions and Cramps, but when they be wholly cut: there foloweth no accidents. Inſomuch that they haue no contrarietie when they retire, the which is manifeſtly ſeen in the woundꝭ of the head, for where the <hi>Pericranium</hi> is but half cut: the accidents are more vehement then when it is wholly cut, as we may dayly ſée by example, when we make inciſion to apply the <hi>Traepan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And amongſt all the hurtes of the <hi>Nerues,</hi> the prickings bringeth moſte pernicious and terrible accidents, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that the orifice is ſo ſmall, that the humour cannot iſſue out, but remaineth within and there gathereth a ſharpnes, whiche drincketh into the <hi>Nerues</hi> and Tendons, and dooth cauſe them to ſwel,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:629:49"/> and by the ſwelling they are ſhortned, wherof commeth ſuche pain, that it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth moſt painful cramps, and ſuch other like accidents as before hath béen ſaid.</p>
            <div type="cures">
               <head>The cure of punctures of the Nerues.</head>
               <p>FOr the curation, there are two things to be conſidered, that is to ſay, to appeaſe the pain, and to defend the parte afflicted from fluxions and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtumation: for the accompliſhing of the whiche, you ſhall applye vpon the wound at the beginning a deſſiccatiue medicine, of a thin and ſuttle ſubſtance, to the end it may penetrate more eaſy the botom of the prick, and conſume the moiſture therin, which other wiſe wold cauſe an egre ſharpneſſe (as afore ſaid) which ſharpnes would bring great pain and accidents. Wherfore you ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply Oil of Turpentine, with a little <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quauitae</hi> wel rectified, or <hi>Euphorbium</hi> and <hi>Sulpher</hi> poudred and incorporated togither, and applyed very warme, or els Oile of <hi>Vitroel</hi> and <hi>Aqua vite,</hi> and round about the place this Cataplaſma folowing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rec. Farine hord. &amp; orrob. ana vnces</hi> 2. <hi>Sirup. acetoſi, vnces</hi> 3. <hi>Flor. Camomil</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:629:50"/> two handfuls. <hi>Lixiuii qui ſufficien. fiat Cataplaſma.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If by this order the paine dooth not ceaſſe, and that there be any contraction of <hi>Nerue:</hi> you ſhall apply ſpeedily hot ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Oil with lint beeing dipt in it, as well at the botome as the edges of the wound, which muſt be doon two or thrée times at one dreſſing, for by this kinde of <hi>Cauterization:</hi> you ſhall ceaſſe the pain, by reaſon of the burning of the Oile, the <hi>Nerues</hi> or Tendons dooth looſe their ſenſible feeling.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the wounds of the ioints.</head>
               <p>THe wounds of the ioynts are for the moſte parte mortall by reaſon of their deneruations or Tendones and membranes, with the which is mingled <hi>Nerues,</hi> for the which cauſe they haue greater feeling, for the <hi>Nerues</hi> beeing mingled with them: cauſeth more pain, which pain bringeth this aforeſaid acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and eſpecially if they be in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior partes, as vnder the arme holes, the bought of the arme, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wriſts or in the hammes, or groynes. By reaſon of the great Vaines, Arteryes and <hi>Nerues</hi> whiche are in thoſe partes, and by the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:629:50"/> meanes of ſolution of continuitie, that are in thoſe partes, cauſeth great pain, flux of blood and other like accidents.</p>
               <p>For the ordering of the whiche: you muſt perſeuer according to the nature of the ſaid accidents, in ſtaying the flux of blood and appeaſing the pain aſmuch as you can poſſible, and if the wound be great: you ſhall ſtitch it leauing an Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in the lower parte therof for to giue iſſue to the matter, this beeing doon: you ſhall apply this poulder folowing the ſpace of ij. or three dayes to preſerue the ſtitches.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rec. Thuris ſanguinis draco. Boli ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menici, terrae ſigil. ana drach</hi> 2. <hi>Aloes, maſt. ana drach.</hi> 1. <hi>fiat puluis ſubtilis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The whiche poulder you ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply vpon the ſeme, and round about the ioint a defenſiue made of the whites of Egges, Oil of Roſes, <hi>Bol, Maſtick</hi> and Barly meale. And if you apply any tent: he muſt be ſhort and not to big, leſt hee ſhould cauſe pain, which tent ſhalbe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed with a diſgeſtiue made with the yolk of an Egge, Oil of Roſes and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſaffron.</p>
               <p>Alſo if the ſaid wound be little and ſtraight (rather then to fal into theſe afor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:629:51"/> accidents) you ſhall inlarge it to the end that the humours which be come to the part (by reaſon of the pain) may haue a large iſſue.</p>
               <p>Moreouer the afflicted part muſt haue reſt and be kept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> colde, and alſo from medicines which dooth relax, ſoften or moiſt, but contrary wiſe they muſt be aſtringant and dry as this <hi>Cataplaſma</hi> folowing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rec. Furfuris maciris, farinae hordei, et fabar. ana vnces.</hi> 4. <hi>Flor. Camomil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le Melliloti ana</hi> half an handful. <hi>Tere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent.</hi> vnces 3 <hi>Mellis communis</hi> vnces 2. <hi>Olei mirh</hi> vnces. 1. <hi>Oximel ſump. vel Oxicrat, vel Lixiuij. qui ſuff. fiat Cataplaſme ad formam pultis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or els this. <hi>Rec.</hi> the lyes of wine, wheat Bran, <hi>Cipres</hi> Nuts, Galles and <hi>Terebenthine,</hi> with this make a <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaſma,</hi> many ſuche other like may bee made, but this ſhall ſuffiſe.</p>
               <p>For thoſe that be applyed on theſe parts muſt reſtrain, dry and corroborate or ſtrengthen the ioints, this dooing you ſhall ceaſſe the pain, and keep the humor from the afflicted parte.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, this is to be noted, that nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther within the wound nor without, you
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:629:51"/> ſhall applye any Oilly or greaſy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, for aſmuch as it relaxeth the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the muſcles, membranes and <hi>Nerues:</hi> by the which meanes it dooth make the place more apt to receiue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluxions. And alſo it dooth ſo relax and moiſten the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that it is a great hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance to the conſolidation.</p>
               <p>Therfore the medicines (which ought to be vſed in this cauſe) muſt be deſicca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and aſtringant as this that folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, which is bothe aſtringant, deſicca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and glutinatiue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rec. Terebint. venic.</hi> vnces 2. <hi>Aqua vitae parum. Pul. aloes. Maſt. mirh, Bol armene ana.</hi> 2. ſcrupples. And ſo applyed as need ſhall require, or ſome other good Balme, beeing applied with deſiccatiue poulder, ſo that the poulder be without a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny ſharpnes, and if there come any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents: it ſhalbe remedied by medicins contrary to the ſame, according as néede ſhall require.</p>
               <p>And this is a principall thing to bee looked vnto, that you keep the wound from colde, the which is all togither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary bothe to wounds and vlcers, by the which menes a great number haue periſhed as <hi>Hippocrates</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hippo. 5. Aphoriſ. 20</note> teſtifieth, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:629:52"/> that to all vlcers the colde is biting, it hardeneth the ſkin, it cauſeth pain and keepeth wounds from ſuppuration, (for aſmuch as it dooth choke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> naturall heat, which ſhould bring ſuppuration) and cauſeth the place to be euil colored: with ſhakings, feuers, conuolſions and exten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions. So that the excrements whiche doo auoid is a glitti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g <hi>Muſceledge,</hi> thin or watriſh humor, which dooth common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly folow in theſe kindes of wounds, for becauſe it is a proper humor that flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth out of theſe wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, for euery place dooth giue his proper humor: as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample the bone beeing broken, the nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of them engendreth a <hi>Calus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this humor whiche commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly iſſueth out of the neruous places, is mix<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed with colde, whiche cauſeth extreme pain, and reſiſteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> medicins, although they be potentiall hot.</p>
               <p>To appeaſe the foreſaid pain, and to correct the intemperature of the colde humor: you ſhall apply warme thinges, not onely potentially: but alſo actually, as a Bullocks bladder béeing half filled with ſome reſolutiue medicin and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or of Bricks beeing made very hot and then quenched in Wine, and ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:629:52"/> about the ioint, and to heat them as often as need ſhall require.</p>
               <p>By this actuall heat, nature is hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to diſgeſt and reſolue the humor con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tained in the place, and dooth ſtrengthen it, for becauſe that the ioynts haue but little heat in them: for the whiche cauſe there be few medicins that wil profit, ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cept they be actually hot. Wherfore I wil conclude that the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the iointꝭ is increaſed rather of colde then of heat.</p>
               <p>For the which cauſe the <hi>Methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> Chirurgian, muſt haue a great reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to theſe wounds, in taking his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of things naturall, not naturall and againſt nature. And moreouer he muſt haue the knowledge how to place the wounded ioints, which ſhalbe ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed héer folowing.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſituation of the wounded Ioint.</head>
                  <p>IF the wound be in the fore parte of the ſhoulder:<note place="margin">This is ment by great wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in the ioints.</note> you ſhall lay vnder the arme hole a Boulſter and cary your arme in a Towel bearing vp the elbow to the end that you may raiſe and holde vp the bone, and ſo to kéep him in his right place, for by this meanes, the glu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tination and conſolidation, ſhall the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:629:53"/> and ſooner be doon.</p>
                  <p>And if the wound be in the lower parte, then when you ſee that nature be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginneth to ingender fleſh, and that the lips of the wound beginneth to cloſe: you ſhall haue good reſpect to cauſe the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent often to lift vp and down his arme, for if you doo forſlewe this, and that the <hi>Cicatrice</hi> be once made: the patient ſhal neuer lift his arme hye, but with great pain.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſituation of the Elbow.</head>
                  <p>IF the wound be in the Ioint of the Elbow, you ſhall ſituate the arme in a meane forme, that is to ſay, neither to ſtraight, nor to muche bowing in, for if the arme be healed in a meane forme: the diſeaſed partie ſhall haue the vſe of it a great deale the better, then other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he ſhould haue had if it had béen to ſtraight or to much bowing in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſituation of the VVriſts.</head>
                  <p>WHen the wound is in the outward or inward parte of the wriſts, or in the ioints of the fingers. The hand and the fingers muſt be ſituated half bowing and you ſhall put within the hand ſome
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:629:53"/> round Ball or compreſſor, for becauſe that if he keep his hands and fingers in a ſtraight forme &amp; nothing bowing: they wil remain without any office, for becauſe that the action of the hand is to take. Wherfore you ſhall obſerue the forme to the half bowing, and hauing the ſaid forme, he ſhalbe able ſomewhat to help him ſelf, in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dling of many things as a ſwoord, Pike, Halbart and the bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del of his Horſe and ſuche other like, which is doon by the action of the hand.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſituation of the Hip.</head>
                  <p>IF the wound be in the Hip, you ſhall vſe ſuch order that the <hi>Os fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar.</hi> doo not come out of his place, the which may be doon by compreſſours and ligatures, and ſo to place the Patient vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on his back vntil ſuch time, as it is gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen to a perfit <hi>Conſolidation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſituation of the Knee.</head>
                  <p>IF the wound bee in the Ioynt of the Knee, the Leg ſhall not be kept ſtraight out: but a little bowing, for if he remain ſtraight: the Patient ſhall go very il, alſo if it be to much bowing in: it wil be to ſhort.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:629:54"/>
                  <head>The ſituation of the Foot or Toes.</head>
                  <p>IF the wound bee in the Ioint of the Foot or Toes: the Patient ſhall keep them out ſtraight, and not cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for if they be any thing bowing: the Patient ſhall neuer go ſo wel as when they bee ſtraight.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:629:54"/>
            <head>A breef gathering to gither of certain errors which the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chirurgians vſe: very neceſſary and profitable for all Chirurgians, which are deſirous to haue the right method of curing.</head>
            <div n="1" type="error">
               <head>The firſt error which they vſe: is touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the diſſeaſe called in Latin, Lues Venerea, and in English the French Pocks.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He errors which</hi> be vſed at this preſent (touching the <hi>Venerian</hi> diſſeaſe) are very great, principally at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, for when it begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it appéereth in the yard with infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, Vlcers and excoriation of the conduict of the Vrine, whiche commeth from the neck of the Bladder. And after that commonly foloweth Apoſtumes of the groynes, with puſſhes and ſuche o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like diſcouloured Pimples accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the infected humor, for the cure of the which, they begin with vehement or ſtrong medicins, as <hi>Colocinthis,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb facs="tcp:629:55"/> of <hi>Hamech</hi> or ſuch like. And the next day folowing they open a Vain in the right or left Arme (reſpecting not that there may folow a Laſk of their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement purgation) and then miniſter their Vnctions and ſuffumigations whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is certainly a manifeſt error.</p>
               <p>By the whiche meanes they drawe the infectious blood and humors to the no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble partes, and féeling the inwarde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyance of the ſame: ſendeth it to diuers outward partes of the body. The which dooth inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der hard tumors as knots and kernels not eaſely curable and moſte ſharp and fretting (rebellions againſt curation) botches with ſuch other like.</p>
               <p>And ſo by the malitiouſnes of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor: it corrupteth and eateth the bone, with ſuch paines and torments that the poore patients are ſo afflicted: that they knowe not where to reſt, and eſpecially more in the night then in the day. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore at this preſent, I haue thought good according to my little ſkil: to teach a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod for to bring theſe errors into a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit order.</p>
               <p>At the begining of this contagious diſſeaſe: you ſhall firſt begin this curati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by euacuating of the body with gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:629:55"/> 
                  <hi>Lenitiues,</hi> which doo bothe coole the boyling rage of the blood: and alſo make it thinner, in mundifying the blood, this muſt be vſed according to the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature of the body,</p>
               <p>The whiche ſhalbe doon after that the body is prepared, to the end that the ſolutiues may the better work vpon the aforeſaid humors. For in this caſe, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture muſt rule the Chirurgion, &amp; not the Chirurgian nature. Then after that: it is neceſſary and profitable to open the Anckle vain, in the right or left foot, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtume dooth appéer &amp; if therbe no apoſtume: according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſcre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of the lerned Chirurgion, this doon: you diuert or pul back y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aforeſaid infecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us humors, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the principall parts. And vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtume, you ſhall apply conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually mollifying &amp; drawing medicins, in dooing what may be to bring him to ſuppuration. This Indicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s beeing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed: you ſhall vſe of the potion made with <hi>Ebenum</hi> &amp; <hi>Guaiacum,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared according to the temperature of the humors, which ſhalbe vſed the ſpace of a moneth or there abouts.</p>
               <p>And although that ſome learned men haue an opinion, that the decoction of
<pb facs="tcp:629:56" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>Guaiacum</hi> ought tobe vſed without any other medicines, yet neuer the leſſe it hath béen found by experience, that the vſe of other Simples with it, (béeing fit and agréeing to the diſeaſes) hath a great deale more profited, &amp; béen found of better effect then if it had béen mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred alone, for in a compound diſſeaſe: a Simple remedy is not requiſit.</p>
               <p>Although that <hi>Alphonſus Ferrus</hi> hath written to the contrary, the which <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> vſeth this decoction of the wood in a manner to all diſſeaſes (whoſe oppi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is not to be folowed) which decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is vſed in <hi>Pthiſi. etiam ſi dies placu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit in ſenio Philippi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer they haue greatly erred, which haue ſet forth the <hi>Radix chim</hi> bée<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing a root very deer, vnprofitable, and all togithers without taſte, and the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt error of all is committed among them, which haue brought in vſe, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et of the decoction of Box trée, whiche is an aſtringant wood, ſtinking and an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to all the principall partes. And if you wil haue a wood whiche is moſte agréeable to the <hi>Guaiacum:</hi> you ſhal vſe of <hi>Fraximus,</hi> the which openeth obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Liuer, of the Melt and of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:629:56"/> the Rains, for I haue knowen many which by the vſe therof haue recouered their helth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="error">
               <head>¶ The ſecond error touching the ſaide diceaſe vvhen it commeth to ſuppuration.</head>
               <p>WHen this diſeaſe hath béen once ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in hand and euil handled, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Ignorance of the Chirurgian or the negligence of the patient: The comon Chirurgians vſe commonly new errors, that is, in giuing ſolutiues with out preparing of the euil humors. By the which meanes they take away the beſt and leaue the worſt behinde, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of ingendreth Nodes, olde and cancard fores, and ſuch like. Then they (as euil or rather wurſſe) apply their vnctions or ſuffumigations before that the vlcers be made clean or the Nodes taken away, and ſomtimes leaue the bone foule. By the which menes they purchaſe to them ſelues both ſhame and infamy, for with in foure or fiue moneths the vlcers open with great corruption of the bone.</p>
               <p>Moreouer they commit an erroure touching the vnction, for they anoint the hed, the Region of the hart, and other no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:629:57"/> partes, againſt all reaſon. And alſo all the whole body ouer, which is the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of many a mans death.</p>
               <p>Therfore to amend theſe errors (when you ſée that this diſſeaſe is confirmed, and that there are hard Vlcers, hard ſwellings or Nodes) it is the moſte ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt way to mundifye the ſaid Vlcers and to open the Nodes with a cawſtick, then you ſhall make inciſion in the node vnto the corruption of the bone, and then apply <hi>Praecipitatum,</hi> or els pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets with <hi>Baſilicon</hi> and <hi>Preſipitatum</hi> mingled togither, this doon: you ſhall take away the corruption of the bone.</p>
               <p>And then after that you may ſafely vſe your vnctions made with <hi>Axungia</hi> Gummes, <hi>Mineralls,</hi> Oiles and <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry,</hi> alſo if you ad thereto of fine Treacle or <hi>Mithridatum,</hi> it wil be the better.</p>
               <p>You ſhall anoint the ſhoulders, the muſcles of the back, the Loines, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hips, the Thighs, the knées, and all the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward members, as Legges and Armes.</p>
               <p>But you muſt take very good héede that you touch not the head, the region of the hart, the Stomack, nor the ridge of the Back. Alſo yee muſt haue a good reſpect to ceaſſe your anointing, in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:629:57"/> ſuche order that you bring not to muche accidents to the mouth, wherby the Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient might vtterly loſe the vſe bothe of his tung and teeth.</p>
               <p>Becauſe that ſo many ignorant Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgians, haue taken vpon them this cure (without either diſcretion in apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vnction, or ordering of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> patient) I haue thought good to write ij, or thrée woords touching the ordering of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</p>
               <p>When the body is prepared of his humors, with apt and méet medicines, aſwel Sirups, <hi>Decoctions,</hi> purgings, and opening of the Vain according to the diſpoſition of the body: the patient ſhalbe placed in a place naturally hot or els otherwiſe made warme, whiche muſt be frée from all colde, hauing the doores, windowes and other open places cloſely ſtopt, for the colde aire is very hurtful bothe for the Sinewy parts, and alſo for the woorking of medicines, for it wil deminiſh &amp; hinder the actions ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And in this caſe ther are many which commit great errors, which are worthy of reprehencion, for aſwel in the winter as in the Summer: they anoint the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients in great and large Chambers,
<pb facs="tcp:629:58"/> where very much ayre entreth.</p>
               <p>Wherfore at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning of this cure (if the place be not very cloſe &amp; warme) you ſhall make a Pauilion with Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and ſuche other like round about a fire, by the which meanes you ſhall keep the colde ayre from the Patient. But if it be poſſible: it is better to haue a little chamber cloſe and warme, and alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually a pan with Coles in the midſt of it.</p>
               <p>If it bee ſo that the Patients be ſo weke that they cannot abide the heat of the fire, or would be loth to be ſéen naked (as women or maids) you ſhall anoint them lying in their beds. Firſt the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient ſhall put out one Arme, and then the other, and ſo the reſt of the partes ſhalbe anointed one after an other. And you ſhall vſe the Patients from time to time according to the diſſeaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="error">
               <head>The third error is concerning wounds pearcing into the Breſt.</head>
               <p>IT fortuneth often times, that the wounds pearce the holownes of the breſt, ſo that great quantitie of blood dooth fall down into the bottome of the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:629:58"/> ſame, and there dooth ſtay vpon the <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phragma,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Diaphrag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ma</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> two muſcles which go <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt &amp; ſeperateth the hart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Liuer.</note> alſo the heuineſſe of the ſaid blood oppreſſeth the <hi>Diaphragma,</hi> and pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trifieth and ingendreth an euill qualti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. The which putrifaction ſending va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours to the hart: cauſeth a continuall fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer, and commonly death within <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. Of the which the common Chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans haue no conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or els by their ignoraunce they knowe not the cauſe, and ſo the Patient is deſtitute of all help.</p>
               <p>Wherfore when you ſée that the wound perceth into the <hi>Thorax</hi> or breſt you ſhal take good aduiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in ſearchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g out diligently, whether the blood be deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended into the lower parte of the <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phragma,</hi> the whiche may bee knowen by the ſtinking of the breath, and by the relation of the Patient, which dooth féele the blood quiuering or ſhaking inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And alſo commonly his face wil be of a reddiſh or hie coulour, by reaſon of the vapours which aſſend vp.</p>
               <p>And note that at the which ſide the blood dooth moſte remaine in lying vpon the ſame ſide: the patient ſhall feel leſſe pain then vpon the other, becauſe that the ſaid blood oppreſſeth the Lungs and the <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phragma,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:629:59"/> the Chirurgian ought to haue a good reſpect to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſignes aboue written, and whilſt that the ſtrength of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> patient is yet remaining: it ſhall bee needful to make way for the ſaid blood to be <hi>Euacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated,</hi> betwéen the fourth &amp; v. rib, a hand breadth or a little more from the Ridge of the back, and your inciſion knife ſhall be very ſharp, alſo you ſhall doo it by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and little very gentlely in cutting <hi>Meſopleuria</hi> or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> muſcles betwéen the ribs, it ought to be doon towarde the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer part of the ſaid muſcles, for the vain whiche nouriſheth them and the liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which giueth them their mouing and féeling: are placed more abooue then belowe.</p>
               <p>After that the inciſion is made: you ſhall let out the corrupted blood by little and little, according to your diſcretion, and it ſhall ſuffiſe to euacuate euery dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſing v. or vi. vnces, this doon: it ſhalbe very profitabe to vſe the wunted potions which you ſhall finde in the writings of learned practitioners which haue large<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly written of the ſaid potions, and by this meanes abooue written: I healed foure in one yéer. The whiche Cures, without the aforeſaid remedyes: could
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:629:59"/> neuer haue béen holpen, for the whiche I giue vnto God moſte harty thanks.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="error">
               <head>¶ The fourth error touching the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of the Traepans Tere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belles, for fractures of the hed.</head>
               <p>IN the fractures of the Skul: there are committed great errors touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the applycation of the <hi>Traepan,</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipally when the bone is broken in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny partes, for they haue no conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſhiuering of the ſkul, but apply the <hi>Trapan,</hi> by the which meanes, they preſſe down the ſhiuers of the bone vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Dura mater,</hi> &amp; rent or tere it in ſuch order that it bringeth great &amp; grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous accidents, wherby commonly deth enſueth. Wherfore in this caſe: you ſhal haue a good conſideration, before that you apply the <hi>Traepan,</hi> for it is better (if it be poſſible) in this caſe to vſe other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tꝭ as Eleuiatories, Ciſers, <hi>Lenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culj</hi> or ſuch other like, to make way for the bruſed matter which depreſſeth the <hi>Duramater,</hi> it ſhalbe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better &amp; leſſe dan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger for the Patient. By this meanes I I haue many times forborne the apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Traepan,</hi> to the profit of my Patients and my good name and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:629:60"/>
               <p>Moreouer there bee many Ignorant Chirurgians which without conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion apply the <hi>Traepan,</hi> vpon all partes of the hed aſwel vpon the comiſtures or ſeames: as other places, whiche is the cauſe of the death of many Patients.</p>
               <p>Wherfore they ought to haue a great conſideration, and to be very diligent in this reſpect, and for to vſe their art accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to the true method.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="error">
               <head>The fift error touching the punctures of Nerues.</head>
               <p>WHen it chaunceth that any is hurt by the punctures of <hi>Nerues,</hi> if hee be not ſpéedily holpen by ſome cunning and expert Chirurgian: hee is in great danger to fall into conuolſions, which is the occaſion of many a mans death whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che commonly chaunceth to them that be dreſt by the Ignorant and common Chirurgians, for when they begin the cure: they make fomentation, with hot water, wherein hath béen boyled Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, Violets and ſuch like, then after the fomentation they apply an appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of pain, made with the crummes of white Bread béeing mingled with the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:629:60"/> yolke of an Egge, Oil of Camomil and Oil of Roſes. The which things are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togither contrary to the Punctures of <hi>Nerues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For aſmuch as their application dooth moiſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to much the <hi>Neruous</hi> places and retaineth or kéepeth in the matter whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is all redy come to the place, and if there be any apoſtume it dooth augment and encreaſe him, and cauſeth the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to aſſend vp to the brain, wherby en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth conuolſion and finally death.</p>
               <p>Wherfore to auoide this daunger, and to follow the cure methodically: you ſhall haue firſt a regarde to the <hi>Euacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the body, and if the ſtrength of the patient be good, to vſe <hi>Flebetonice Reuolſiue</hi> or according to the cauſe of the gréef. Then (to take a way that whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is redy conioinct) you ſhall enlarge the <hi>Orofice,</hi> to the end that the medicin may the better penetrate to the bottom, and take away the ſharpnes of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor. In this caſe I haue found very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiitable the Oil of <hi>Hippiricon</hi> prepared in this forme that is to ſay with <hi>Venice</hi> Turpentine, and for one vnce of the ſaid Oil, you ſhall take half a ſcrupple of <hi>Euphorbium,</hi> which ſhalbe applyed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:629:61"/> hot with pledgets, &amp; vpon that a Plai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter made with <hi>Propolis, Gum ammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niack</hi> and Wax aſmuch as ſhall ſuffiſe. By this meanes the matter (which is drunk into the <hi>Nerues</hi> or tendons) ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be drawen out to the outwarde partes.</p>
               <p>Alſo for this intent I haue found pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Linſeed Oile and <hi>Enphorbium</hi> of eche like muche, with the xx. parte of <hi>Sulpher</hi> béeing very finely poudred, with <hi>Peroſin</hi> and wax as much as ſhall ſuffice to make an Vnguent.</p>
               <p>This Vnguent dooth heat moderatly, attract and diſſicate and is of a ſubtil fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie, with the which (by the help of God) the Chirurgians ſhall get bothe honor and profit,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="error">
               <head>The ſixth error is touching the abuſe of the runners about called cutters for the ſtone and Ruptors.</head>
               <p>AMong the common Runnees a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout (which vſe to cut for the ſtone and <hi>Ruptures</hi>) is vſed a great abuſe and to be lamented of any chriſtian hart, for vnder this cure of cutting the <hi>Hernyes</hi> they doo miſerably take away the ſtone aſwell in the <hi>Hernia aquoſa</hi> or <hi>vento<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſa</hi> as in all the reſt, the which is vnman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:629:61"/> and againſt the wil of God, and they doo not only vſe it in men, but moſte of all in little Children, therfore it ſhould be very good for the parents which haue their Children in any maner of wayes troubled with any kinde of <hi>Hernies,</hi> that before they commit their Children to léeſe their ſtones, and ſome times liues, by any of theſe that bee Runnagates, (for ſo may I wel terme them) that they ſhew them to ſome learned Chirurgian to the end that he may ſée what kinde of <hi>Hernies</hi> they haue, and ſo to diſcerne the <hi>Aquoſa</hi> or <hi>Ventoſa,</hi> from <hi>Inteſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nale</hi> or <hi>Omentales.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For certainly I haue ſéen <hi>Hernies</hi> in childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which came by the relaxaſion or deuiſion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Peretoneu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> haue been perfit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly healed by the apt applying of glutina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue medicins &amp; ſuch otherlike, without cutting or taking away of the <hi>Teſticle.</hi> But ſuch is the couetouſe deſire of theſe Runners whiche make the parents be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue that it cannot bee helped without their butcherly cutting, and for to intrap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mony, for they be as greedy after it as a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny liuing thing is after their pray, not hauing the fear of God before their eies, but like gréedy gripers catch what they
<pb facs="tcp:629:62"/> may for the time, and care not what become of them afterwardes, whether they liue or die, wee haue had it by experience of them what harme they haue doon bothe by the murdering cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and alſo laming with continual pain, for when they come ruſhing into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and haue ſuche a great name at their firſt comming. But after when their woorkꝭ be tried and then the proof of them ſeen: the people for the moſte parte are wery of them, and many a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe childe and widdow which they haue made: may lament the time that euer they knewe them, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (which is not a few) bide tormentꝭ and pain by the dealing with them. I dare affirme they neuer did any cure in this Realme but that there be Engliſh men which haue doon the like and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>Suche is the foliſh fantaſyes of our Engliſh nation that if he bee a Straun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: he ſhall haue more fauourers then an Engliſh man, though the Engliſh mans knowledge doo far paſſe the others as experience therin hath ſhewed, and this I wil ſtand to the proof that ther be Engliſh men that ſhall in all things doo
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:629:62"/> aſmuch bothe by learning and experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as any of them all. Paraduenture you wil obiect and ſay, that there be Straun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers which haue doon cures which ſome Engliſh men haue refuſed, I wil graunt that it may be ſo, for there bee a great many of vnlearned Chirurgians which take vpon them the art, &amp; look what they doo it is by blinde chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and ſo through their blindenes ſome are marred, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by after it falls to a ſtraungers chaunce to doo it, and then it is giuen out that all the Chirurgia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in London could not doo it, and ſo the whole company is defamed and euil thought of, but I could ſhewe to the contrary, where the ſtraungers haue left and could not doo, Engliſh men haue doon it diuers times: which if néed be I can bring the proof and no ſmall ſort, whiche to name I will omit til another time more meet. And now to return to the matter, ſée how long any of theſe cut<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters doo tarry in a place, ſome a quarter of a yéere, ſome half, and none ſcant a yéer, for it wil bee to hot for them: for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their beaſtlines is once knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: then they muſt ſeek a new place, for if they ſhould tary in one place they would bee hated like mad Dogs, &amp; that they knowe
<pb facs="tcp:629:63"/> wel inough. Now for becauſe that they ſhall not deceiue the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people with their fair promiſes: I wil write all the kindes of <hi>Ruptures</hi> or burſtings and how to knowe euery one of them to the end that if any Chirurgia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which hath not the knowledge, may ſtraight at the firſt ſight knowe what may be doon, and ſo to enforme the parents of the Children the trueth of it, &amp; what the Cutter may doo in it, for moſte commonly they bee ſo ignorant that they knowe not the one from the other, therfore as I haue ſaid before, it is néedfull for the Patients to haue an expert chirurgia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to aprooue him and ſée whether hee be able to fulfill that which he promiſeth or no. Now I will begin to treat of the kindes of <hi>Ruptures</hi> and firſt I wil begin with the deuiſion of them in generall and then perticulerly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the viij. kindes of Hernies.</head>
               <p>THere be eight kindes of <hi>Hernies</hi> or <hi>Ruptures</hi> wherof ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e haue their pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per names: and the others by ſimilitude, the proper <hi>Hernies</hi> doo moſte commonly come by the relaxaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or <hi>Rupture,</hi> of the <hi>Pretoneu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> inſomuch that the <hi>Inteſtines</hi> and <hi>Epiploco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> or <hi>zirbus</hi> dooth looſe their
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:629:63"/> naturall place, and of theſe are vij. kindꝭ, that is <hi>Enterocele</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nie Inteſtinale, Epiplocele</hi> or <hi>Hernie Zirbale, Bubonocele</hi> or <hi>Hernie Ingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nale,</hi> the <hi>hernies</hi> by ſimilitude are whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is ſome tumor againſt nature in the Cods or in ſome parte of the Groin, without the comming foorth of the <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> or <hi>Zirbus,</hi> and of theſe there are v. kindes, the firſt is called <hi>Hernie A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queuſe</hi> and of the Gréeks <hi>Hidrocele,</hi> the ſecond <hi>hernie Charneuſe</hi> or <hi>Sarcocele,</hi> the third: <hi>Variqueſe,</hi> the fourth <hi>Vente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe</hi> which is called of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gréeks <hi>Pneuma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tocele,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fifth <hi>Humorale,</hi> whiche ſhalbe ſpoken of pertitulerly in order, and firſt we wil begin with the proper kindes.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the hernie Inteſtinale.</head>
                  <p>FOr becauſe that the <hi>hernie Inteſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nale</hi> is the moſte conuenienteſt, I wil ſpeake firſt of it. This kinde is no other then a certain deſcending down of the <hi>Inteſtines</hi> in <hi>Scrotum,</hi> the cauſe of the whiche is when the <hi>Peretoneum</hi> is broken or relaxed in the place wher the <hi>Spermatike</hi> veſſels doo paſſe, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s commonly by ſome vehement ſtrain, as by vehement running, leaping, lifting,
<pb facs="tcp:629:64"/> or vehement crying, and ſuch other like, the ſignes to knowe when the <hi>Inteſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> is deſcended into <hi>Scrotum,</hi> is when he lyes, they wil eaſely be put vp again without any maner trouble, or may bee reduced the patient ſtanding with ones hands, and in the reduſing you ſhall hear a gurguling or noiſe, &amp; by this you may knowe it from <hi>Zirbus</hi> becauſe that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>zirbus</hi> is put vp it makes no noiſe, and alſo it is not ſo painfull: the other ſignes ſhalbe declared when we come to ſpeak of the <hi>hernie Zirbale.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When this kinde is not very farre gone, and that it be not complet: the beſt way is to cure it by medicines, aſwel to be taken inwards: as to be applyed with out, that is to ſay with emplaiſters and ſo by conuenient truſſing and boulſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſtipt in the Iuce of herbes conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for <hi>Ruptures</hi> which are of aſtringa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and glutinatiue facultie. I haue ſeen ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny by theſe afore ſaid medicines haue béen perfectly cured, yet neuertheleſſe if for the oldenes of it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it be not tobe cured by theſe menes: then you muſt come to the laſt remedy which is by cutting, for the executing of the whiche I wiſh all men to chuſe an expert woorkman, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:629:64"/> not to truſt to much to theſe runners a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and as for this kinde it may be cut without taking away of the <hi>Teſticle.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of hernie Zirbale.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HErnie Zirbale</hi> whiche the Gréeks doo call <hi>Epiplocele,</hi> is a nother thing then the falling of <hi>zirbus</hi> (whiche is a grece that couereth the Guts) into <hi>Scro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> the which moſte commonly falles within <hi>Didimes,</hi> but yet ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times by the breaking of the <hi>Didimes</hi> it falls out, the cauſes aſwel inwarde as outwarde are the ſame which cauſe <hi>hernie Inteſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le,</hi> for look how the <hi>Peretoneum</hi> is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or relaxed in the other: euen ſo dooth it in this, the ſignes are much like alſo, ſauing that it is much more ſofter, for in the touching it handleth like wul, and is alſo leſſe painful, and it is more difficult to put vp the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>hernie Inteſtinale,</hi> and in the reduſing makes no noiſe, this kinde is leſſe dangerous then the others by reaſon that the pain is leſſe and alſo for becauſe that the excrement is not in it as it is in the <hi>hernie Inteſtinale.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now héer is a ſpeciall thing tobe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this kinde, which the common cut<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters doo vſe, that is, they doo vſe to cut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb facs="tcp:629:65"/> the <hi>zirbus</hi> whiche is deſcended within <hi>Didime</hi> without either tying or cautriſing, and ſo there foloweth a flux of blood which hauing no iſſue but is retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the belly there dooth corrupt whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che cauſeth moſt perilous accidents and moſte commonly the death.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the relaxacion of the Peretonium called hernie Inguinale.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HErnie Inguinale</hi> is a deſcending of the <hi>Inteſtines</hi> or <hi>zirbus</hi> into the Groynes, which the Latins cal: <hi>Ingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> the which ſort dooth neuer go further then the Groin, for when the <hi>Inteſtines</hi> or <hi>zirbus</hi> dooth paſſe thorow the <hi>Pereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neum:</hi> then is it either <hi>Inteſtinale</hi> or <hi>zirbale,</hi> for this kinde is nothing but a relaxacion of the <hi>Peretoneum.</hi> The cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes are as of the others aforeſaid, and it is eaſely to be knowen by the roundnes, and it will be more eaſely reduced then any of the others, you may knowe when the <hi>Inteſtins</hi> is deſcended by noiſe that it wil make, though not commonly: yet moſte oftenneſt as hath béen ſaid of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terocele,</hi> but if it be the <hi>zirbus</hi> it makes no noiſe, and is much more ſofter and not ſo great pain.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:629:65"/>
                  <head>Of the kindes of Hernies which be by ſimilitudes or improperly called.</head>
                  <p>HEertofore we haue ſpoken of thoſe thrée kindes of <hi>hernie</hi> whiche are properly called, now it remains to ſpeak of the fiue kindes whiche are by ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, &amp; firſt we wil begin with the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoſe,</hi> whiche is no other thing then a certain watriſh tumor of <hi>Croton</hi> increa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced by little and little, &amp; for the moſt part lies betwéen <hi>heritroides</hi> and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sperma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tike veſſels, how beit ſome times it may be contained betwéen <hi>Dartos</hi> and <hi>heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troides</hi> and betwéen <hi>Dartos</hi> &amp; the <hi>Scro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum</hi> as many learned men haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, the ſignes are, that the <hi>Scrotu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> doth wax big by little and little and for the moſte parte without pain, and the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more is heauy and gliſtering and hard principally when the <hi>Scrotum</hi> is filled: it waxes in length and dooth not return as doth the <hi>Inteſtinale</hi> and <hi>zirbale</hi> but remaines at one ſtay.</p>
                  <p>This kinde if that the water, haue long line there and ſo corrupted the <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticle:</hi> it muſt be taken away.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of hernie Charneuſe.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:629:66"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HErnie Charneuſe</hi> which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gréekꝭ doo cal <hi>Sarcocele</hi> is a tumor againſt nature in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Scrotum</hi> which there dooth grow to a certain ſcireuſe fleſh, and dooth much reſemble the <hi>Verequeſes</hi> or ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Vaines, the cauſes of the which are by the gathering togithers of abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance of groſe humors, whiche nature cannot rule becauſe of the weaknes, the ſignes are an vnequable hardenes, and infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which dooth alwaies remain in the parte that is to ſay the <hi>Dideme,</hi> and doth alwaies increace with pain béeing vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall and not euen, wherefore <hi>Guido</hi> ſaith that this kinde and <hi>Vanqueuſe</hi> ar very dangerous.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Hernie Verequeſe,</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HErnie Verequeſe</hi> is an appéera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Vaines not accuſtomed about the <hi>Teſticles</hi> and other partes contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with in <hi>Scrotu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> The cauſes ar groſe humors gathered togithers as melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colike blood and ſuch like, whiche nature cannot diſparce becauſe of wekeneſſe. The ſignes are, replecion of the vaines about like to the Twigs of Vines with ſoftnes of the <hi>Teſticle</hi> or <hi>Dideme.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This kinde if it be not very great and far
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:629:66"/> gone it may be healed by ſolutiue medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The hernie Ventoſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HErnie Ventoſe</hi> is a tumor of the cods increaced of a windines, the cauſe is of the imbeſility or weaknes of the parte, and is knowen by the ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Coddes and yard, and gliſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth like vnto a ſlikt paper, which comes ſudainly and is round and light, ſo that there be not another humour adioyned with it,</p>
                  <p>This is to be cured with <hi>Carnificatiues</hi> as <hi>Oleum nucum, Oleum Anethinum, Coſtinum &amp;c.</hi> and there may be added to of Séeds and hearbes, as <hi>Semen, ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi, Carui, Faeniculi, Agni caſti, Ruta, Calaminta, Origani. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Hernie Humorale.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HErnie Humorale</hi> is an Apoſtume contained likwiſe in the cods whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is ingendred of humors hot and colde not muche declining from his naturall habite, which may lye betwéen <hi>Scrotum</hi> and <hi>Dartos</hi> or betwéen <hi>heritroydes</hi> and <hi>Dartos</hi> or onely within <hi>heritroydes,</hi> as for the cauſes, ſignes and curation are
<pb facs="tcp:629:67"/> like to other Apoſtumes.</p>
                  <p>Now that I haue declared the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, cauſes and ſignes of <hi>hernies:</hi> it ſhall not be amiſſe to expound in few woords thoſe parts which muſt be opened when any of theſe kindes muſt be cured by han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy operation, and this is tobe noted firſt, that the <hi>Teſticles</hi> are couered with three <hi>Tunicles,</hi> the firſt of them takes his ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of the ſkin &amp; is called <hi>Scrotum</hi> or purſſe, the ſecond which takes his origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of the <hi>Peretoneu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> and is called <hi>Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos,</hi> the third whiche is proper to the ſaid <hi>Teſticle</hi> and is called <hi>Heritroydes,</hi> theſe two laſt doo not onely couer the <hi>Teſticles</hi> but alſo the Spermatike veſſels, aſwell they whiche bring the ſubſtance where with the Sperme is made which are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Preparans:</hi> as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which bring the Sperme to the neck of the bladder which is called <hi>Eiaculatoires</hi> or expelling, the which goes vp to <hi>Oſepubis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the waights and meſures vſed in Chirurgery.</head>
               <p>HEer gentle Reader I thought good to declare certain waights and me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſures for the better vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of this
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:629:67"/> book of <hi>Galens</hi> and all other of his woorks to the end that yung Studients in this art ſhould haue none occaſion of let fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the perfit vnderſtanding of it, and firſt I wil ſhew you how they were called in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde time of the Greekꝭ &amp; alſo of the Romains and as neer as I can how muche euery one dooth contain according to our mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And as for the names of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimples: I thought it good to write them in the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tin</hi> as they were, for by the ſearching of their engliſh names: the Reader ſhall ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry much profit, and another cauſe is that I would not haue euery ignorant aſſe to be made a Chirurgian by my Book, for they would doo more harme with it then good.</p>
               <p>Firſt <hi>Mina</hi> which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gréeks call <hi>Mna,</hi> there are of diuers ſortes, for ſome are <hi>Romain</hi> others <hi>Attique,</hi> others <hi>Egipti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enne,</hi> others <hi>Alexandrine,</hi> but <hi>Romains</hi> is according to <hi>Paulus Aegineta</hi> and <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lens</hi> 16. vnces.</p>
               <p>The pound according to the <hi>Romains</hi> is 12. vnces.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Attique</hi> and <hi>Egiptienne</hi> is .16. vnces.</p>
               <p>The vnce whiche is the 12. parte of a pound is 8. Drams.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:629:68"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deunx</hi> is 11. vnces, which are .264. Scrupples, that is, 2. third partes and 1. fourth parte of a pound.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dextans</hi> is the half and the third part of a pound, that is to ſay 10. vnces and 240. Scrupples, <hi>Vitruuius</hi> in his third Booke ſaith that it is the meaſure of ten Inches.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dodrans</hi> is the half and one quarter of a pound, which is 230. Scrupples, <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truuius</hi> in his Book afore ſaid dooth call <hi>Dodrans</hi> the meaſure of 12. Inches.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bis</hi> is 2. third partes which is 8. vnces and 240. Scrupples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sextunx</hi> is 1. half and 1. twelf parte that is 7. vnces and 168. Scrupples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Selibra</hi> is half a pound or <hi>Semis,</hi> and 144. Scrupples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quincunx</hi> is 5. vnces.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Triens</hi> is the 3. parte of a pound which is 4. vnces and 120. Scrupples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quadrans</hi> is the 4. parte of a pound which is 3. vnces and 72. Scrupples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sextans</hi> is the 6. part of a pound whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is 2. vnces and 48. Scrupples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vnſia</hi> is to ſay an vnce whiche is 8. Drams.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Semiuncia</hi> is half an vnce.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Denarius</hi> or <hi>Drachma</hi> is the 8. parte
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:629:68"/> of an vnce and is 3. Scrupples which the Gréeks call <hi>Grammata</hi> that is xxiiij. let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the Gréek, and the vnce hath as many Scrupples as the Gréek hath let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p>Scrupple is as it were the beginning of all waights as an introduction and is 2. <hi>Oboles,</hi> an <hi>Oboles</hi> is 2. <hi>Siliques,</hi> and a <hi>Silique</hi> 2. <hi>Chalces,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Chalces</hi> is 8. Graines.</p>
               <p>The pound of liquid things as Wine, Oile, and ſuch like, was in <hi>Roome</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by a veſſel of Horne whiche had xij. rundels about it, and euery one of them did ſignifie an vnce, and was called a me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſured pound, <hi>Galen</hi> makes mention in his firſt book <hi>Decom. medic. ſecundum genera,</hi> in the making of the white plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amphora</hi> of the <hi>Italy</hi> meaſure, dooth contain 72. pound of Oile, and of Wine 80, and of Hunny 108. the Hunny is the 4. parte more heuyer then is the wine, and the half more then Oile</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ceranium</hi> is of Wine and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagre 80. pound, and of Oile 72. pound, and of Hunny 120. pound.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Vrne</hi> is of wine &amp; vinagre 40. l. of Oil 36. l. and of Hunny 60. pound.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:629:69"/>
               <p>The <hi>Conge</hi> is of Wine and Vinagre 10. pound, of Oil 9. pound, and of Hunny 15. pound.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Seſtier</hi> is of Wine and Vina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre 1. pound. 8. vnces, of Oil, 1. pound, and of Hunny 2. pound</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hemine</hi> is of Wine and Vina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gre 10. vnces of Oile. 9. vnces, and of Hunny 1. pound.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Cotile</hi> is of Wine and Vina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre, 10. vnces of Oile 9. vnces, and of Hunny 1. pound.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Oxibaphus</hi> is of Wine and Vinagre 18. Drams, of Oile 18. Drams, and of Hunny 27. Drams.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Acetabule</hi> is of Wine and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagre .18. Drams, of Oile 18. Drams, and of Hunny 27. Drams.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ciath</hi> is of Wine and Vinagre 12. Drams and 4. Scrupples, of Oile. 18 Drams, and of Hunny 20. Drams.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Cheme</hi> is of wine &amp; Vinagre 3. Drams and one Scrupple and of Oile 3. Drams, and of Hunny 5. Drams.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end of waights and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the auncient writers.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:629:69"/>
            <head>¶ Faults eſcaped in the Printing.</head>
            <p>¶ Note wheras you finde this letter (a) that dooth ſignifie the firſt ſide of the leaf, and this letter (b) the ſecond ſide.</p>
            <p>In the firſt page, read (the third Book of <hi>Galen</hi> of the compoſition of medicines in general). Then in the firſt page of the Epiſtle to the Reader the xij. &amp; xvi. lines, for iudications read (indications).</p>
            <p>In the 11. leaf a. the xiij. and xiiij, lines read <hi>(drachmas)</hi> for <hi>drachmas,</hi> &amp; <hi>(Opo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponacis)</hi> for <hi>Apoponax.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 14. leaf a. and the xix, line read (the ſixth he dooth) for he dooth vi. looſe.</p>
            <p>In the 26. leaf a. and the vi. line read, <hi>(Maron)</hi> for <hi>Maron.</hi> And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xij. line of the ſame read <hi>(phou ideſt)</hi> for <hi>phoud eſt</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 27. leaf a. the xviij. line. red (the childes pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts did ſend for <hi>Galen</hi>) for, did ſend him to <hi>Galen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 30. leaf a the firſt line read (Paps or Breſts) for, Dugs.</p>
            <p>In the 31. leaf a. the iiij. and v. line leue out, the whole and ſound partes.</p>
            <p>In the 33. leaf b. the xv. line read <hi>(Olei mirtiles)</hi> for, <hi>Olei mirh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 36 leaf a. the iij. line read (bowing for, lowing.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:629:70"/>
            <p>In the 38. leaf a. the xvi. line read (no apoſtume in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> groin: then acording) for Apoſtume: according.</p>
            <p>In the 41. leaf a the iiij. line read (qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie) for, qualtitie. And in b. the xxiij. line (read wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d potions) for, wunted potions Fo. 47. line .6. read, is none other thing,</p>
            <p>Gentle Reader I shall moſt hartely deſire thee that if in the reading this work other faults you finde then heer is noted not rashly to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne the Author for aſſure your ſelf that by his wil none should haue eſcaped, and though the Printer be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo careful, yet in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſome wil eſcape.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale</salute>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London at the</hi> long Shop adioyning vnto <hi>Saint Mildreds Church in the</hi> Pultrie, by Iohn Alde.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="laudatory_poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:629:70"/>
            <head>¶ Octoſtichon Ioannis Baniſteri Nottinghamienſis medicae &amp; Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgicae artis profeſſoris in lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem medicinae.</head>
            <l>Miramur crebro medicos molimine claros,</l>
            <l>corpora praeceptis noſtra iuuare ſuis.</l>
            <l>Eccé quót aſſidué ſcribu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hinc inde libellos,</l>
            <l>in laudes artis docte Galene tuae.</l>
            <l>Hanc et maiores, hanc et coluere minores,</l>
            <l>hijs confert magna parte, Bakerus opem</l>
            <l>Cuius ab ingenio prodit, vigili<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> labore,</l>
            <l>vtilis iſte liber, dignus &amp; ipſe legi.</l>
            <l>Hanc artem docuit, vaſto qui preſidet orbi,</l>
            <l>ſaepius hanc laudat filius ipſe dei.</l>
            <l>Haec viſum caecis, mutis parat iſta loquelam</l>
            <l>hac audit ſurdus, claudus et hac graditur.</l>
            <l>Hac redit in vitam, vitali lumine caſſus,</l>
            <l>viuere qua vidi, qui moriturus erat.</l>
            <l>huic ergo fauea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, iunctis vmbonibꝰ omnes</l>
            <l>et ſimul huic himnos voce ſtilo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ferant.</l>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:629:71"/>
            <head>¶ Tetrastichon eiuſdem in librum Bakeri.</head>
            <l>¶ Miſtica magnoperé quicun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Chirurgica</l>
            <l>huc debes poſita ſaepe venire mora.</l>
            <l>Hac ſtudij fructus: doctiſſima multa videbis captas</l>
            <l>abdita quae longo delituere die.</l>
            <l>At nunc ſic lucent, vt ſi laudare pararem,</l>
            <l>in mare tunc videar, fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dere ineptus aquas</l>
            <l>Ergo Bakere tuum ſuperabit ſidera nomen,</l>
            <l>at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> aliqua ſemper parte ſuperſtes eris.</l>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="encomium">
            <head>Gulielmi Clowei, Chirurgi Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donienſis carmen encomiaſtichon ad ſuum ſtudioſum Georgium Bakerum.</head>
            <l>Laudibus egregiis efferri pulchra ſolebant,</l>
            <l>nec praeclara, ſua laude carere decet.</l>
            <l>Quantos idcirco poſcat Bakerus honores,</l>
            <l>hoc opere exacto, dicito muſa mihi.</l>
            <l>Te tua ſedulitas tranſfert ad laudis honore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</l>
            <l>Et tua te virtus inclyta ad aſtra vehit.</l>
            <l>Tu magni Hippocratis reſeras tu tecte Galeni</l>
            <l>A tantis ad nos nobile ducis opus.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:629:71"/>
            <l>Anglia, quas fraudes tibi nunc ſmalkaldia ferret</l>
            <l>Bakeri clarum ſi latuiſſet opus.</l>
            <l>Ergo quiſquis Apollinias ſectabitur artes,</l>
            <l>Bakerum celebret, nocte dieque meum.</l>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="acrostic_encomium">
            <l>
               <hi>G</hi> Good cauſe of prayſe you doo deſerue,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>E</hi> euertly to ſet foorth:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>O</hi> Olde woorks of Fathers wiſe and graue,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>R</hi> report dooth ſhowe is troth.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>G</hi> Giue foorth the ſame with ſpéedynes,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>E</hi> encline your whole indeuer:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>B</hi> Beholde you not what praiſe it is,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>A</hi> a man to liue for euer.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>K</hi> Knowing that ſo the wiſe doo wright,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>E</hi> earth though they truely be:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>R</hi> Reuiue again by Books in ſight,</l>
            <l>who ſo wil read may ſée.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>ꝙ <hi>William Clowes Chirurgian.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
